<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A table-booke for princes Containing short remembrances for the gouernment of themselues and their empire. Wherein also respectiuely the seuerall members of state, and all sorts of subiects, may finde matter worthy their obseruation. By Patricke Scot, Esquire.</title>
            <author>Scot, Patrick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 118 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852086</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852086</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17391</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17391)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1256:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A table-booke for princes Containing short remembrances for the gouernment of themselues and their empire. Wherein also respectiuely the seuerall members of state, and all sorts of subiects, may finde matter worthy their obseruation. By Patricke Scot, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Scot, Patrick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 113, 110-215, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop, dwelling in Distaffe-Lane at the signe of the Dolphin, neere Olde Fish-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A table booke for princes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Education of princes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:1"/>
            <p>A TABLE-BOOKE FOR PRINCES.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING SHORT Remembrances for the Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>of themſelues and their</hi> EMPIRE.</p>
            <p>Wherein alſo reſpectiuely the ſeuerall Members of State, and all ſorts of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, may finde matter worthy <hi>their obſeruation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Patricke Scot,</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <q>Nihil recte inchoatur, niſi poſt Deum fauerit Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perator, nec quenquam oportet vel meliora ſcire vel plura quam principem, cuius doctrina omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus poteſt prodeſſe ſubiectis.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Veget. in Prol.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by BERNARD ALSOP, dwelling in Diſtaffe-Lane at the Signe of the Dolphin, neere Olde Fiſh-ſtreet. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, the hopefull Prince <hi>of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F PHILLIP of <hi>Macedon</hi> did yeelde no leſſe thankes to his falſe gods, that his Sonne <hi>Alexander</hi> was borne in the time of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> then in bleſſing him with ſo hopefull a child: your Highneſſe hath iuſt cauſe to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the Name of the true God, that you are the Sonne and Heire of a Mightie King, and of a Religious, Wiſe, and Learned Father, who (beſides the appointing of godly and learned Tutors) in his owne
<pb facs="tcp:17391:3"/> perſon, (exceeding <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> both in the Theoricke and Practicke of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment) hath ſo ſeaſoned your Highneſſe tender yeares, with the (Giliadlike) odoriferous Balme of Diuine and Morall inſtructions, as the ſweete perfume thereof hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready rauiſhed the hearts of all loyall Subiects, with the extreamitie of ioy; and one day (by Gods Grace) will make knowne to the World, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe you haue in your birth-right, but the perfection of happineſſe in ſuch a Father, who hath ſo emptyed the profound Ocean of Diuine and Humane learning, that (except bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the rich Treaſure of his ſtore, nothing that belongs to the true inſtitution of young <hi>Alexander,</hi> can either be found or added.</p>
            <p>Wherefore SIR, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your Highneſſe to cenſure theſe lame Eſſaies of my barren braine (or rather crums falne from the Princely Table of your more then Salomon-like Father) as the Widowlike Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boll
<pb facs="tcp:17391:3"/> of my deuotion; pleadge of my Faith, or Subiect to try your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, clemencie in pardoning, or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in condemning of me, who haue raſhly perſumed to prefer my <hi>home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpun labours</hi> to ſo powerfull a <hi>Mece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> whoſe approbation or diſlike may enrich me with the fulneſſe of content, or expoſe me vpon the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Rockes of vntimely ſorrow. But SIR, either in life or death I ſhall be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe humble and true Seruant, <hi>PATRICK SCOT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:4"/>
            <head>TO THE GENEROVS READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowing (Generous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that theſe ill dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted labours of mine, ſhal be as well expoſed to the byting cenſure of baſe and enuious Criticks, (whoſe peruerſe and obſtinate diſpoſition hath taught them to detract from others, and forget their owne obliquities) as to the view of High borne, true, Noble, and generous Spirits, (whoſe birth and education in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites them to looke with a more fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſpect vpon the weake endeuours of good meaning.) For thy better ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I am to aduertiſe thee; that at my firſt ſeizing vpon this Subiect, (a task I grant farre aboue my reach) I did not
<pb facs="tcp:17391:5"/> iealouſly ſuſpect, but altogether diſtruſt my owne inſufficiencie; and therefore did make choyce rather to looſe my thus ſpent time, and commit my confuſed Papers to a fiery tryall, then to be the Herald of my owne ignorance: hut when I had better aduiſed, I did finde that the Supreame King is well pleaſed with the leaſt dram of true deuotion: that his Vicegerents ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Monarches, and braue Princes haue taken in good part, the ſmaleſt oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their meaneſt Seruants: that euery good ſubiect (amongſt whom in loyaltie I am inferior to none) are by the moſt ſtrict bonds of allegiance tyed, to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate their talent to the ſeruice of their Prince and Countrey: then (I ſay) I did recall my fire-threatning ſentence, and was content that this obortiue birth ſhould come vnto the world; But vpon aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (leaſt thou ſhould expect more then I promiſe) that the Tytle of a <hi>Table-Booke</hi> might be Charactered vpon the front is piece thereof: which very name, enforceth rather a neceſſitous vſe for memory, then an elaborat intire deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb facs="tcp:17391:5"/> or methodicall diſpoſition of the matter.</p>
            <p>Sith then I hold vp my hand at the bar of thy iudgement, I intreate that this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe (blemiſhed with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polliſhed ornaments of Art) may be ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered vnder the wings of thy fauorable cenſure, and the rather becauſe this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect is more neerely aliyed to truth and ſinceritie, then to art and affectation. So ſhall I remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy conſtant welwiller, <hi>P. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:6"/>
            <head>AVTHOR LIBELLO.</head>
            <l>EIa, age nunc, roſeaſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> genas, frontem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſerenam</l>
            <l>Oſtendas Coelo; licet immaturè, nec omni</l>
            <l>Parte, ſatis vel comptè ſinus, collecteue pulchram</l>
            <l>Caeſariem in nodum; tamen hand fortaſſe, libelle,</l>
            <l>Monſtrum immane tuens: te libertatis amicae</l>
            <l>Munere te placitâ donabit ſepe ſalute</l>
            <l>Magnanimus Carlus; magni generoſa propago</l>
            <l>Patris, qui Centum numerans ab origene Reges</l>
            <l>Omnes ſceptriferos, omnes decora alta ferentes,</l>
            <l>Bis feſe quartum adiungit: Bodotria ſolum</l>
            <l>Quem dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Tamiſiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> colit. piſcoſa<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> bannae</l>
            <l>Flumina, tu gratum venies caput omnibus illis</l>
            <l>Queis magè ſana bonus finxit praecordia Titan</l>
            <l>Et non Antyciras opus eſt dare lintea: verum</l>
            <l>Momorum damnanda, boniſque aduerſa propago,</l>
            <l>Et qui vipereum ſpirant ex ore venenum,</l>
            <l>Zoilous, atque Theon, te ſannis omnibus vnum</l>
            <l>Excipient; durum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> prement, liuoris acerbi</l>
            <l>Morſibus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Interea tu quâ licet, vtere ſorte</l>
            <l>Suppliciter venerare atque admirare potentem</l>
            <l>Parcere Subiectis &amp; debellare ſuperbos.</l>
            <l>Et (ſi quem) ſolum ſubmiſſo poplite Carlum</l>
            <l>Qui (quanuis talem) vultu haud dignatur amico</l>
            <l>Cernere te. Charis grates hinc ſoluere amicis</l>
            <l>Sis memor: &amp; labes veteres, fractique vigoris</l>
            <l>diſiectum robur, non inficiatè, recedas.</l>
            <l>Denique quae Momus iaculatur ſpicula, ſorti</l>
            <l>Sperne animo; ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vim quae ea dextra mittat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tundo.</l>
            <l>Vel ſpacium euadet totum: vel perforet ictum.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:6"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Sect. 1.</label>
               <item>OF the condition and true happineſſe of Princes.</item>
               <label>Sect. 2.</label>
               <item>What benefit commeth to a Prince, by good education and learning.</item>
               <label>Sect. 3.</label>
               <item>Of the vertuous life of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: of the election of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, Officers, and Seruants.</item>
               <label>Sect. 4.</label>
               <item>What generall obſeruations the happy and quiet Gouernment of a Prince requireth.</item>
               <label>Sect. 5.</label>
               <item>By what meanes the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous minds of Princes are knowne.</item>
               <label>Sect. 6.</label>
               <item>Of Nobilitie.</item>
               <label>Sect. 7.</label>
               <item>Antidotes againſt the poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of vaine glorie, and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoughts, that intoxicates the minds of young Princes.</item>
               <label>Sect. 8.</label>
               <item>How Princes ought to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate their power.</item>
               <label>Sect. 9.</label>
               <item>Whoſe Image good and bad Princes repreſent: by what E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithetes
<pb facs="tcp:17391:7"/> they are knowne, and of their ſeuerall actions.</item>
               <label>Sect. 10.</label>
               <item>By what meanes a Prince may ſecure himſelfe in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and obtaine the loue of his Subiects.</item>
               <label>Sect. 11.</label>
               <item>Princes ought to be eaſie in giuing acceſſe, and ready to heare the complaints of the oppreſſed &amp; poore.</item>
               <label>Sect. 12.</label>
               <item>Of the neceſſity of Princes knowledge in the affaires of their Empire, and preſence (ſo farre as is poſſible) in the adminiſtration of Iuſtice.</item>
               <label>Sect. 13.</label>
               <item>Of Lawes and Iuſtice.</item>
               <label>Sect. 14.</label>
               <item>Of the wrath of Princes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and how they ſhould puniſh.</item>
               <label>Sect. 15.</label>
               <item>Of two ſorts of flattery, but chiefely of the laſt, that haunts the Courts of Princes.</item>
               <label>Sect. 16.</label>
               <item>To whom Princes may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commit publike functions.</item>
               <label>Sect. 17.</label>
               <item>Of ſecrecy, in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of the weightie affaires of Princes, and what iudicious policy
<pb facs="tcp:17391:7"/> Princes may ſomtimes lawfully vſe.</item>
               <label>Sect. 18.</label>
               <item>Vpon whom Eccleſiaſticall functions, by Princes are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred.</item>
               <label>Sect. 19.</label>
               <item>Of Church Controuerſies, ciuill contentions, ſeditious Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, infamous Libels, and with what care they are to be repreſſed.</item>
               <label>Sect. 20.</label>
               <item>Of the liberality of Princes.</item>
               <label>Sect. 21.</label>
               <item>Of the mutuall friendſhip and correſpondence, that ought to be betwixt neighbouring Princes, and contiguous Kingdomes.</item>
               <label>Sect. 22.</label>
               <item>Of warre, what Princes are to conſider before they enter in warre: for what cauſes they may lawfully take armes, and how to behaue themſelues in warre.</item>
               <label>Sect. 23.</label>
               <item>Of Souldiers, and military diſcipline.</item>
               <label>Sect. 24.</label>
               <item>Of the meditation and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Princes againſt the day of their death.</item>
               <label>Sect. 25.</label>
               <item>Of mourning for the dead, and of Chriſtian and Princely bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17391:8"/>
            <head>A TABLE BOOKE <hi>FOR PRINCES.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. I.</hi> Of the condition and true happineſſe of Princes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey are either blind or ignorant,<note place="margin">Vulgus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doctum, &amp; multorum illa capitam bellua per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, magnos principes regno ſuo, velut in a maeniſſimo quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſo viue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, vbi dijs hominibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que plaude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, omnia quae ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litias perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſuppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditantur. Reinh. Lor. Hacla.</note> that (with the vulgar) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimates the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Kings to conſiſt in titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar honours, largeneſſe of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, millions of Subiects, faire Palaces, multitude of attendants, rich treaſures, and other gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſhewes: They neuer looke into the heauie burthen and thorny cares of gouernment, whereof a diademe is compoſed, wherein the ſuppreſſing of vice, the exalting of vertue, equall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17391:9"/> of Iuſtice; immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately in their owne perſons, and mediately by their deligates: the defence of the poore and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the carefull ouerwatching that neither in themſelues, nor in orhers the lawes bee infringed, are chiefe and inſeparable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of Empire, and annexed to Crownes, vpon no leſſe perill then priuation of all thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Epithets, which are due to good Princes here, and of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall reward that is promiſed hereafter.</p>
               <p>This kingly charge, outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glorious,<note place="margin">Plut. in. vit. Solon. Plutar. an ſeni geren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſit reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. Macrob. lib. 1. cap. 16.</note> begun with cares, continued with feares, oft times ended with ſorrowes, rightly conſidered, will make <hi>Seleucus</hi> with ſighes bewaile the miſeries of Kings: <hi>Damocles</hi> leaue to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17391:9"/> 
                  <hi>Dioniſius:</hi> Golden <hi>Craeſus</hi> in ſorrow and admiration remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber old <hi>Solon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let therefore all Princes, who are tranſported with the libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous deſire of raigne, or ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enlarging of their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wiſely expend the reaſons following: Firſt,<note place="margin">O nobilem magis quam foelice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, quem ſi quis poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſeat qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multis ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citudinibus &amp; periculis ſit refertus, ne humi iacentem capere vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let. Val. Max. lib. 7. cap. 2.</note> the great charge that is impoſed vpon thoſe to whom gouernment is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: how difficill it is to exerciſe the ſame rightly: what wiſdome is required of Princes leaſt they make ſhipracke of their priuate, and publike ſtate: how farre they ought in vertue excell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: that the publike good is as peculiar to Kings, as ſeeing to the eye, or hearing to the eare: That none ought to aſpire to that ſacred ſeat, but ſuch who in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17391:10"/> goodneſſe imitates the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, whoſe throne it is which they enioy.<note place="margin">Plut. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. Prin.</note> 
                  <hi>Est Principis Vnicum munus alijs proſpicere &amp; publicis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulere commodis; id autem non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt niſi ſapientia, vigilantia, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mique integritate ceteros antecel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eraſ. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. Prin.</note>Secondly, they are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſceptors are not giuen vnto Kings (tyrant-like) to abuſe their authority, but to be ſtrickt obſeruers, of the lawes they imp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vpon others:<note place="margin">Principatus nihil aliud ſunt quam ſplendida miniſteria. Eraſ. apo. 5.</note> That the duty of Kings and ſubiects (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes then in the dignity of commanding, and that Kings are onely countable to God) is mutuall, <hi>Principi populus cenſum debet, debet obſequium, debet hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem; populo viciſcim Princeps debet clementiam; debet vigilantiam.</hi> O
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17391:10"/> King (ſaith <hi>Agapetus</hi> to <hi>Iuſtinian</hi>) ſith there is none vpon earth able to command thee,<note place="margin">Ad Iuſtini. Caeſ.</note> impoſe an neceſſity of keeping the lawes vpon thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">Plut. in ap</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exaſperate by an offence of high quality (ouercome with the violence of his paſſions) did pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh a young man, contrary to the law hee had made; and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him cry out,<note place="margin">Crimen li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet per ſe graue erat tum admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum in Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doluit exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta non ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum legem propriam vindicta. Suet. in Caeſ.</note> O <hi>Caeſar</hi> I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to the law which thou haſt made, did ſo condole the exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of puniſhment, not due be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore legall cenſure, that hee did forbeare to take food; vntill ſuch time as hee had fully teſtified the greatneſſe of his conceiued ſorrow: a notable example in a great Prince to whom the breach of law hee had made was ſo diſpleaſant,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17391:11"/> that he ſtudied rather to puniſh his owne error; then the offence of ſo high quality,<note place="margin">Plut. de doct. Prin.</note> committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his royall dignitie: hee did well know, that the law is the ſoueraigne queene of diuine and humane gouernment: that it is not enough to make lawes, but to keepe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Principes miniſtri dei ſunt ad cura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſalutem hominum, vt bonaquae Deus illis largitur, parum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribuant, pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. Plut. de doct. Prin. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. li. 2. fol. 101.</note>Thirdly, let ambitious <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> and tyranous <hi>Dioniſius</hi> (whoſe ruling appetite, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, on world and humane blood cannot ſatiate) conſider that Kinges are the images of God; that as God is goodneſſe it ſelfe, and diſtributes his goodnes to all men: ſo Princes (Gods vicegerants) ought to bee profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to their ſubiects: not to preferre their priuate gaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the publike good, but to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17391:11"/> drawe their picture by the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of their Maker, and ſo ſhine before their people, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning of vice, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vertue, as they exceed them in place and dignity.<note place="margin">Si quiſpiam nauta mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit, affert nauiga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus nocumentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed ſi naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gator ipſe delirauerit, totius efficit nauig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Agap. ad Iuſt.</note> Let Princes wiſely weigh that the helme of the Common-wealth is committed to their charge, and that they are countable for the well or ill gouernment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: That there is nothing more contagious, or that ſooner diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeth through the body of ſtate, then the example of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whoſe liues are ſo conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as the ſunne, and therefore to the good of all men they muſt be the beſt amongſt men, or to the preiudice of all, and their owne the moſt wicked.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the boyling deſire
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17391:12"/> of Empire will growe cold,<note place="margin">Iacob. Mag. Brit. &amp;c. Rex: in Epiſt ad Carol. Prin. Suet. in Fla. dom.</note> if Princes ſet before their eyes, the infinite dangers to which they are ſubiect; to what burthen they are tyed, how full of thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cares, and commonly how ſhort the life of greatneſſe is. It was not without cauſe that <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> did complaine, vpon the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of Princes, ſubiect to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious machinations,<note place="margin">Conditio Principum miſerima eſt, vbi timentur infidiae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditoriae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fraudes, doli, editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiae, vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. Reinh. Lor.</note> deteſtable treaſons, deceitfull conſpiracyes, and intoxicate poyſonings: they cannot in ſafety goe abroad, without a guard, neyther take meate before ſome other taſte it: they muſt in peace liue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not onely againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion of forraine enemyes, but inteſtine and domeſticke friendes: one betrayes them, another deceiues them: others
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17391:12"/> flatters them: they are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of all diſcourſe; the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of all mens eyes: from all which the vulgar are ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:<note place="margin">Nulla enim aconita bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus, tunc illa time, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pocula ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata, &amp; lato ſitinum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debit in auro: Iuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Sat. 10.</note> they are neither ſubiect to feares, nor feared or enuied of any: their earthen cups yeeld them drinke to quench their thirſt, but not to extinguiſh their life: hunger makes their browne bread ſweete, labour their ſleepe quiet, ſmall fire keepes them from cold, courſe clothes ſhelters their nakednes, and an innocent life crownes their death.</p>
               <p>By which it is euident that Princes muſt eyther acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the weight of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, what intricate difficulties and dangers are in the right exerciſing thereof; that they are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17391:13"/> ſet vpon the theater of the world,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Epiſt.</note> or (tyrant like) reſolue that the Common-wealth, muſt be the ſtage of their inſolent life, and wiſhed for death. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall toyles whereunto Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ſubiect, made <hi>Caeſar</hi> oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wiſh to bee exonered of ſo heauy a burthen;<note place="margin">Reinh. Lor.</note> hath beene the cauſe that many wiſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Princes haue preferred, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate life, before publike great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iacob. mag. Brit. &amp;c. Rex de i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naugurat. Prin. fol. 122.</note>Laſtly, let the ſerious medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſtrict accompt that Princes muſt giue, ſerue to curbe the inſolent affecting of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the time will ſhortly come (death ſparing no more Kings than beggars) when hee muſt yeeld vp his accompts (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the greatneſſe of his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17391:13"/> talent) before ſuch a Iudge,<note place="margin">Vidi mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os magnos, &amp; puſillos ſtantes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſpectu throni. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. 20.</note> from whom all the Monarches in the world are not able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale; and whom they cannot deterre, deceiue, or corrupt: what ſtrickt account will hee take? what ſeuere iudgment will hee pronounce againſt ſuch as either haue vniuſtly vſurped his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,<note place="margin">Omne ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi vitium tanto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectius in ſe crimen habet, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to maior qui peccat habetur Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Sat. 8.</note> or being lawfully placed in his throne vpon earth, haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded themſelues, or not acquit them of the truſt committed to them? <hi>Agapetus Iustinianum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monuit, vt talem ſe preſtaret erga ſubditos vt famulos, qualem Deum futurum erga ſe exoptaret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is then manifeſt that good Princes (to whom the inceſſant care of then charge is more deare, then the mad and fooliſh deſire of preheminence) are not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17391:14"/> happy by the externall ſhadowes of greatneſſe, but by ſhewing themſelues great, in ouerruling their diſordered affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (which is none of the leaſt, but rather the perfection of humane acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) and then in the eſtabliſhing and keeping of good lawes:<note place="margin">Eraſ. inſtit. Prin.</note> in the adminiſtration of Iuſtice; in rewarding the vertuous and puniſhing the vicious: in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting the humble, obedient, and beating downe the proud oppreſſours: in repreſſing of enemies and cheriſhing of friendes: in puniſhing treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable practiſes, and deteſting inpoſturing flattery: in chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing detractions, and diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing hollow-hearted hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Epiſt.</note> and finally to bee ſuch, as they care not who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17391:14"/> looke vnto their moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret actions, or outward ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
               <p>Theſe and the like bee true kingly functions, the rich iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells that adornes diademes, and are the happineſſe of Kinges, not conſiſting in temporary, momentary pleaſures, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull vices: but vpon the neuer periſhing delights, that are builded vpon the vnremoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able rocke of vertue, vnto which no man can aſcend, but by the ſteppes of diuine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.<note place="margin">1. Reg. c. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> (in whoſe choiſe it was to aske what hee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) did well know that this was the ladder by which <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> did reach vp to heauen, and the life of kingly maieſty; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he did not aske riches, vaine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17391:15"/> glory or worldly pleaſures; but wiſedome; neither worldly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but ſuch whereby in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe and vnderſtanding he might execute his royall functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Eraſ. apo. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous that his ſonne <hi>Alexander</hi> ſhould not giue his mind to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible riches, but to the ſtudy of philoſophy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reinh. Loc.</note>Theſe great Princes did wiſely inform the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, that wiſedome and learning are the <hi>Herculian</hi> pillars of Kings, without which their conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (although embelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the glory of <hi>Salomon</hi> the Empire of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the armies of <hi>Xerxes,</hi> the riches of <hi>Craeſus,</hi> and other whatſoeuer vanities na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth produce, or art inuent) is more miſerable then the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt <hi>Codrus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ludo. Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. lib. 1.</note> or diſpiſed <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17391:15"/>
               <p>It is then religious wiſedome, ſeconded by good education &amp; learning, that dignifies Princes in their youth, accompanies them in their life, and glorifies them after death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O vitae religio conſeruatrix, tu coelitus demiſſa interris, animos vera virtute imples; tu diuinarum hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manarumque rectrix: tu imperia, ſceptra, iudicia, vt firma, vt legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima ſunt facis: tu priuatorum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunam moderaris: tu populos in fide ac officio contines: in te vna bene beateque viuendi firmamentum exiſtit: demum nihil in Principe nec populo praeclarum eſt, quod non a te ortum ducat, tuoque illuſtratur ſplendore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17391:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. II.</hi> What benefit commeth to a Prince, by good education and learning.</head>
               <p>AS the moſt fertill ground, without culture,<note place="margin">Eraſ de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. Prin.</note> is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly barren in the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of wholſome fruits, but doth ouergrowe with thiſtles and hurtfull weedes. So the minde of man without education, is not onely infertill in the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of vertue, but naturally inclined to bring foorth igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, voluptuouſneſſe, and all other vices.<note place="margin">Prou. 22.15</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that fooliſhneſſe is tied to the heart of a young man,<note place="margin">Nemo naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens ſed fit. Senec. de ira</note> and cannot bee vntied but by inſtruction. There is no man borne good, neither
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17391:16"/> Prince, howſoeuer nobly deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, without wholſome doctrine, did prooue himſelfe worthy of Empire.</p>
               <p>It concerneth therfore gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, high borne, and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Princes,<note place="margin">Cic. 2. Tuſc. quaeſt:</note> to follow the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of good letters, to honour loue, and retaine the profeſſors of liberall Arts, and to bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in them: The benefits thereof are many, the effects admirable, and the reward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable.</p>
               <p>Firſt, vertuous education be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth a habit of vertue,<note place="margin">Aelian: Lamp.</note> and hatred of vice, for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more certaine, then that thereby a man beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth more then a man, and participates in the diuine nature; on the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17391:17"/> other ſide,<note place="margin">Plut. de e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duca puer.</note> if he be left to his naturall ignorance, he degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates to all wickedneſſe, and ſimpathiſeth rather with the moſt ſauage and rude beaſts, then with reaſonable men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucurgus</hi> the Spartan law-giuer, made manifeſt the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfulneſſe of education, by the diuers effects of two puppies. <hi>Duo catuli ijſdem parentibus orti, caeterum diuerſam vitae conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem aſſecuti, alter guloſus, alter venator euaſere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, although Princes ſo exceed all others in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of all things,<note place="margin">Eraſ. 3. apo.</note> that learning may ſeeme either to ſerue them to ſmall vſe, or not neceſſary at all: yet for many weightie conſiderations, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17391:17"/> more powerfull they are,<note place="margin">Principes opus habent multis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis, vt ſanctè vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; vt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terem cum ſuis ad fecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Adamú rerum copia luxuiante<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, coerceant; ne volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frangantur, &amp; inſoleſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ad interitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Gregor. moral.</note> the leſſe able they are, to gouerne either themſelues, or their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple without knowledge and learning; being more ready to decline from the right hand of vertue, vnto the left hand of vice, then to keepe the ſure way, neuer knowne to the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and vnlearned. Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is that ſtrong guard, that defendeth Princes againſt the deceitfull inticements of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, power, honour, riches, and whatſoeuer elſe praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates greatneſſe (blindfolded in the <hi>Cimerian</hi> darkeneſſe of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance) to an irrecouerable downefal: a Prince ought not to meaſure his happineſſe by thoſe falſe goods of fortune,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17391:18"/> but by the true riches of his minde,<note place="margin">Polib. lib. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Gorgias</hi> being asked, whether he did thinke the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian King happy or not, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, he did not know how vertuous and learned hee was; for, ſaid hee, there is no happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in theſe things that may be taken away.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Libri muti magiſtri neſcientes erubeſcere non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuent, vt dignos hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s laudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus euehu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; ita prauos dente theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino rodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Quint. de lect. lib.</note>Thirdly, learning ſtirres vp and excitates the minde and loue of a Prince, to the reading of bookes, wherein hee may learn al things needful for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or ſubiects. Theſe dumbe maſters will praiſe him if he be worthy, or without feare, with the Prophet tell him; Thou art the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: They wil finally (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bluſhing) admoniſh him of thoſe things, his Courteors ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17391:18"/> will not, or dare not: The want of learning is the cauſe that Princes reiect the counſell of their friends, and contemne the power of their enemies; ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance cauſed <hi>Cambiſes</hi> cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to murther the ſon of <hi>Prax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſpes</hi> his ſeruant,<note place="margin">Senec. de ira.</note> for his faithful councell; Tyrannous <hi>Dioniſius</hi> to checke <hi>Plato</hi> for his louing aduice.<note place="margin">Plut. apo.</note> 
                  <hi>verba tua inquit Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, otioſorum ſenum ſunt, &amp; tua inquit Plato, tirannum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe &amp; the like Phalariſme examples of tyranny,<note place="margin">Reinh. Lor.</note> prooue that the knowledge of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is neceſſary for good Princes; that thereby they become ſo much better, that they willingly embrace ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17391:19"/> and come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of themſelues. <hi>Omnes boni principes, de quibus legitur, vel fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt per ſe ſtudioſi, vel habuerunt ſapientes ad inſtruendum eos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, although by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, nobility of blood, and indulgence of fortune, Princes are emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: yet to adde a more ſhining brightneſſe to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſplendor,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 21.</note> learning is neceſſary, <hi>Doctrina eſt ornamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum aureum prudenti &amp; quaſi bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiale in dextro.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, learning is an honour to all men,<note place="margin">Ex Doct. Gerh. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam.</note> ſaith <hi>Meander:</hi> many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Princes at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, haue beene more reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced for their learning, then honoured for their greatneſſe.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, learning onely brings
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17391:19"/> with it laſting,<note place="margin">Cicero in Senec.</note> and Prince worthy pleaſures, the reſt are but deceitful momentary, baits to inſnare them: <hi>Gaudia falſa non remanent, ſed fugitiua volant, quod leuius videretur, ſi fugientia non relinquerent at ergo venenum.</hi> Theſe falſe pleaſures are right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly named (by <hi>Architas</hi>) the moſt deſtroying plagues inflicted vpon men.<note place="margin">Martial. l. 2:</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was wont to admoniſh his ſchollars not to looke vpon pleaſures at their comming, but in their going, for in the one (ſaid he,) they ſhew faire, in the other they leaue ſorrow and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>On the contrary, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights that are begotten of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and vertue, are true ioyes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17391:20"/> permanent pleaſures, the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of youth, the crowne of age; They adorne proſperity, vphold aduerſity,<note place="margin">Cicero pro Arch.</note> at home are the beſt ſtewards, abroad the beſt interpreters, in peace the vſhers of idleneſſe, in warre the Marſhals of campes, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the miniſters of diſcourſe, and alone priuate and true Councellours.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. offic.</note>Noble <hi>Affricanus</hi> vſed oft to ſay, that he was neuer leſſe ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, then when ſolitary.</p>
               <p>A Prince of <hi>Athens,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what he did profit by Philoſophy,<note place="margin">Diog. Laert.</note> anſwered; That at all times hee could without offence, conferre with himſelfe, and in euery diſcourſe drawe a concluſion conſonant to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17391:20"/> Beſides, ſayd hee, the knowledge of Philoſophy, makes mee loue wiſe learned honeſt men, deteſt flattering Paraſites, and fooles.</p>
               <p>Sixthly,<note place="margin">Gelli l. 13.</note> learning adornes a Prince with curteſie, clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and meekeneſſe; The firſt begetteth inſeparable loue, the ſecond humane admiration; and the third diuine applauſe. The loue of ſubiects, is the wall of kingdomes. Mercy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſheth the throne of a King, and meekeneſſe deifies him.<note place="margin">Horat. 2. Epiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Omnis eruditio manſuetos facit, nemo enim adeo ferus, vt non miteſſere poſsit, ſi modo doctrinae patientem praebeat aurem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seauenthly, in moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate diſeaſes (by learning a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17391:21"/> Prince findes matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and preſent helpe. This was the medicine that <hi>Marcus Tullius</hi> did miniſter to his friend.<note place="margin">Epiſt. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. lib. 6.</note> O <hi>Balbus,</hi> ſaid hee, if I could preſcribe better medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine for our equall griefes,<note place="margin">Siquidem ſtudia vt optime foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollunt; ita facilime ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitates minuunt. Senec. de conſol. ad Albinum.</note> I would; ſuch as I can, I will: let the ſtudy of good letters, which for our delight we haue formerly embraced, bee now the comfort of our miſeries, and laſt health: as they did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance our better fortunes; ſo they will mitigate preſent ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, cure our wounds, and ſo expell melancholy paſſions, that the ſorrow of humane mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, ſhall haue no further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try then to the gates of our weakeſt ſences.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17391:21"/>
               <p>Since therefore humane mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, are no leſſe incident to Princes then poore men, they ought by learning to arme themſelues againſt the violent batteries of aduerſe fortune. If <hi>Craeſus</hi> had participated either in learning, or aduiſe with <hi>Solon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quanto maior eſt fortuna, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to minor eſt ſecura. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt. ethni.</note> in his flouriſhing eſtate, he had found more comfort thereby vpon his tragicall theater, then in the millions of his golden treaſures. <hi>Dioniſius</hi> (nothing inferiour to <hi>Craeſus</hi> in tyranny or preſumption;<note place="margin">Licet Regi affectu fieri philoſophu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Plut. in apo.</note> but ſuperiour by learning; in his exile, being asked what he had learned by <hi>Plato:</hi> anſwered, that by Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy he had learned to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe equally the eſtate of a Prince, and beggar.<note place="margin">Gellius l. 2.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17391:22"/>
               <p>Eightly, a learned Prince doth willingly enolyne to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vertue,<note place="margin">Gellius l. 2.</note> he followeth the one, &amp; ſhunneth the other, not for feare, but for loue of themſelues. The Cubiculars of the Perſian Kings, were enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euery morning to put their maſter in minde of his kingly office, by theſe wordes: Ariſe O King, and goe about the publike affaires:<note place="margin">Heron. ad Heliod.</note> A learned Prince needeth no ſuch aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement,<note place="margin">Philoſophi ponu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor ſpecies perturbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, metu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpem, Leti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, quibus hominum vulgus, vt procelloſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mare flucti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur Ariſt. pol.</note> before hee goeth to bed hee premeditates the next dayes worke, in his bed hee conſults vpon it, and at his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing hee executes his ſetled deſignes; hee is neither ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, with ſorrow, feare, hope, ioy, and other vulgar violent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17391:22"/> perturbations, but willingly followes thoſe wholeſome lawes he doth enact for others. <hi>Aristotle</hi> being demanded what hee had profited by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, anſwered; That hee had learned to doe thoſe things willingly, that others did for feare of the Law.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Oderunt peccare boni virtutis amore,</l>
                  <l>Oderunt peccare mali formidine poenae.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Ninthly, giuing of anſwers,<note place="margin">Eloquentia principibus magno or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namento eſt Cic. 4. de finib.</note> vſing perſwaſions, reſoluing of queſtions, diſcourſing of lawes, conferring of honours, defence of things propoſed, or done, are inſeparably an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the office of a King: vnto all which, hee muſt bee by learning inabled, leſt hee expoſe himſelfe to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17391:23"/> cenſure of ignorance, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſubiect of ſmothered laughter and future contempt. The words of a Prince are (like the oracles of <hi>Apollo</hi>) no ſooner ſpoken,<note place="margin">Plato. de rep.</note> but taken holde of by all men: therfore great care is to be taken, that his wordes, his orations, his anſweres and demandes, be conſonant to the to the dignity of a Prince. <hi>Plato</hi> did pronounce the ſtate hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, where a wiſe and learned King did raigne; for ſaid hee, learning is the only and chiefe happineſſe, and ignorance the greateſt ill: vpon the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends all humane felicity;<note place="margin">Iſocrates ad Demoniac.</note> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the laſt aſſured miſery. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtippus</hi> made choyſe, rather to bee a begger, then vnlearned,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17391:23"/> becauſe by the one hee wanted onely externall and temporall riches, but by the other huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, knowledge, and endleſſe wealth. <hi>Sola omnium poſſeſsionum immortalis ſcientia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore (to conclude this point) learning keepes ſtates from returning to their former <hi>Chaos</hi> of confuſion;<note place="margin">Cic. pro Arch.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Aug. ſuper pſal. 101.</note> it is the ſun that enlightens the minde of Princes, and being remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, gouernment by diſorder, turnes into tyranny, and is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured with the darke cloudes of ignorance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphonſus Aragonum Rex, cum audiſſet quendam dixiſſe non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere principem ſcire literas, fertur exclamaſſe: eam vocem bouis eſſe non hominis, cum a rationis iuditio
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17391:24"/> non profecta, ſed inſulſo belluinae ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatis instinctu fuiſſet effuſa.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. III.</hi> Of the vertuous life of Princes: of the election of their Councellors, officers, and ſeruants.</head>
               <p>THere be three inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companions that ought to accompany Princes;<note place="margin">Impera ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi, impera ſeruis, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Sociad.</note> Firſt, the care of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; Secondly, the care of their ſubiects, Thirdly, the care and iudicious choyce of Councellours,<note place="margin">Virtutes Principis per omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperiorum corpora dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funduntur. Senec. de Clement.</note> officers, and ſeruants. The firſt is the rule whereby the ſecond and third are ſquared; the good life of a Prince, is the fountaine from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17391:24"/> whence the waters of life, of countrey, city, and court flow: The Prince is the head, they the members, he is of no leſſe force in their politicke body, then the head in a naturall; which being craſie or diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, imparts ſickneſſe or death to the weaker parts; Princes are of ſtar-like influence vpon inferiour bodies; If the ayre bee infected with an epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call quality, they that dwell therein cannot be very ſound: If Princes bee giuen to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vertue, the ſubiects and ſeruants like apes imitate them; if vicious,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Epiſt. Ex Plut.</note> they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in all licenciouſneſſe and inſolency. This exemplary life of Princes was the ground-ſtone
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17391:25"/> whereon <hi>Platoes</hi> Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke was builded;<note place="margin">Fla. vopiſc. in aurel.</note> old <hi>Solons</hi> faithfull counſell to Princes, was to goe before their people in vertue and goodnes, which precedency is the maintainer of piety, honeſty, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: <hi>Secundum iudicem populi ſic &amp; miniſtri eius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.2.</note> ſaith the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Philoſtrat. lib. 9.</note>The Annals of all nations demonſtrate, that whatſoeuer vertues or vices Princes haue followed, ſuch were the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes from whence the life of ſubiectes and ſeruants were drawne.<note place="margin">Ex dione caſsio. lib. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Efficaciſsimum eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortationis genus Principem hoc facere quod ab alijs fieri velit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this perſonall care is the firſt royall wiſedome, and the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17391:25"/> frame of good gouernment;<note place="margin">Opera dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, vt &amp; Princeps ſuos mores integros &amp; incorruptos praeſtet rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae &amp; quoad licet omnes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos, proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, aulicos ac miniſtros ſui ſimiles habeat. Eraſ. in ſtit prin.</note> ſo is the wiſe election and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king choyce of counſell and helpes (for ſupporting the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy burthen of a diadem) the next neighbouring vertue. <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt Principem non poſſe ſua ſcientia cuncta complecti, ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conciliari eorum quae inter homines ſunt diuiniſsimum est.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Princes then are firſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with that ſupreme King by whom they raigne; hee is <hi>Magni conſilij Angelus; admirabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis conſiliarius:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 9.6. Humana conſilia ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigantur, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtibus praeferu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur. Max. lib. 1.</note> without this counſell all other is erronious and full of danger. <hi>Dauid conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebat dominum antequam facta ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua agrediretur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next vnto diuine conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the helpe of counſellours
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17391:26"/> and fit perſons (for ſeconding ſo weightie a charge) offereth it ſelfe to the iudicious view of Princes, and wherein the following cognizances are to be obſerued: Firſt, that ſuch as are admitted, to ſo honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a place, bee religious fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. 3. de offic.</note> and of vpright life, <hi>Conſiliorum gubernaculum lex diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; in conſilijs acquirendis pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum adiungit vitae probitas:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,<note place="margin">Principi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſule non dulciora ſed optima So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. apud Laert.</note> that they be <hi>fidi rerum hominumque periti,</hi> faithfull in counſell, skilful in affayres and conditions of people. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they be free of flattery; <hi>tantum nocet adulatio in conſilijs, quantum veritas conſilij.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they may bee wiſe, graue, well affected and ſeene
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17391:26"/> in matters of State, of good experience, and ſuch as by their various fortunes haue learned the art of counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:<note place="margin">Ioan. Pall. par. 1. ca. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Mihi fortuna multis rebus ereptis, vſum dedit bene ſuadendi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Mithridates.</hi> Fifthly, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours muſt bee calme and humble, (euer ſhunning foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ambition and downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing pride.<note place="margin">Conſulta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari veloci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere autem tarde Ariſt. Eth 6. Conſiliarij ſint ſtabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſolidi. ne monean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, timore: amore, vel cupiditate, in conſilijs dandis, lib. 5. Hiſtor. tripart.</note>) But well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed and free in deliuering their counſell, and full of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in the execution of thoſe things, that doe concerne the weale of their Soueraigne and ſtate. Sixthly, they are to bee conſtant in their actions and deliberations; <hi>Prudens &amp; ſapiens non ſemperit vno gradu, tamen ſemperit vna
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17391:27"/> via.</hi> Seuenthly, that they be modeſt in their geſture and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; <hi>Nullius ſeruilis ſententiae ſponte authores, &amp; quoties ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitas ingrueret prudenter mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Adeo oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebatur co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium apud Romanos, vt arcana Patrum conſcripta multis ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis nemo Senatorum enunciaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Val. lib: 3. cap. 5.</note>Laſtly, becauſe ſecrecy is the key of the rich cabinet, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in counſell is incloſed, Kings are to bee carefull that their councellours bee ſecret and cloſe in matters conſulted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Taciturnitas optimum atque tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimum rerum gerendarum vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, quia res magnae non poſſunt ſustineri ab eo cui tacere graue eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe be the rare rich robes, wherein councellours are to be inueſted; whereof Princes are to take ſuch notice that none be admitted to ſo eminent dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17391:27"/> without their wedding garments:<note place="margin">Conſiliari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us tibi ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnus ex mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Eccleſ. 6.</note> That (if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) they may bee eyther well knowne to the Prince, or by his diligent inquiry tryed by the touchſtone of good fame. <hi>Singuli decipere &amp; decipi poſſunt, nemo omnes neminem omnes fefelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> Next vnto the election of councellours, ſucceedeth the choyce of followers, officers, and ſeruants; wherein there qualities, places, and number is to bee conſidered: For the firſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> King <hi>Dauid</hi> leadeth the way to ſucceeding Kings: <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulans in via Domini mihi mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrabit;</hi> Let them be of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the land, vertuous, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and honeſt in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their places, bending
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17391:28"/> all their ſtudies promptly,<note place="margin">Plat. 7. de rep. Ariſt. 5. 6. Pol. Thucid. 6. Plut. in Pol.</note> care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to aduance the weale and honour of their Soueraigne; they that are in moſt eminent places, and neereſt to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Kings, as they ought to be well educated, generouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclined, endued with wit and diſcretion: ſo muſt they not thinke that all men are borne for them, and they for no man; but that the loue they owe to their countrey, tyes them (as feeling members of one body) modeſtly, and in a fit time to offer vp the griefes, or reaſonable ſuites of ſuch ſubiects whoſe condition, or place, admits them not to the preſence of Princes.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, wiſedome aduiſeth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17391:28"/> all ſort of followers of Princes, (from the Cedars to the ſhrubs) to ſhun ſoftneſſe, delicacy,<note place="margin">Et qui mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia geſtant in domibus regum ſunt, Math. 12. Has pofun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das vitioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> radices e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellat prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps. Et Colloq. Ger. Nou. Agricol. in prouerb. Ger.</note> and idleneſſe; to abandon all ſuch vices as are the poyſon of Countrey and Court: Such are Atheiſme, blaſphemies, volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe, flattery, detraction, hypocriſie, &amp; other ſuch ſtaines of Court, as <hi>Agricola</hi> wiſheth to bee farre remooued from the Courts of Chriſtan Princes; &amp; which he pointeth out thus:
<q>
                     <l>Fides, honeſtas, humilitas, ac veritas</l>
                     <l>Pudor decens, &amp; mentis alma caſtitas,</l>
                     <l>Simplex nitentis pectoris prudentia,</l>
                     <l>Integritas, &amp; omne virtutis iubar:</l>
                     <l>Ex principum modo palatijs procul</l>
                     <l>Fugere quorum (proh dolor) vices gerunt</l>
                     <l>Fraus aetra, perfidia, procacitas, ſales,</l>
                     <l>Calumniae, palpatio, ronchi, doli,</l>
                     <l>Naeſuta ſanna, ſcomma, ludus aleae,</l>
                     <l>Potationum crebra concertatio</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:17391:29"/>
                     <l>Summi nihil dei metus perpenditur,</l>
                     <l>Curatur &amp; nihil reſpectius vltimi</l>
                     <l>Fati, nihil tormenta dira tartari.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt obſeruation is in the number of attendants and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,<note place="margin">Quint. Curt.</note> wherein Princes (with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>) may more ſafely make choyce of few and ſufficient,<note place="margin">Ael. Spart. Minus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iucunda eſt aula, quam infinita fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulorum maximè ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uilium ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitum, para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conum &amp; ſcurrarum multitudo complet. Eraſ. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. Prin.</note> then (with <hi>Xerxes</hi>) of confuſed multitude of paraſites, falſe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, or ignorant followers, and the reaſons be theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, as the moſt populous feaſt (although moſt ſuptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepared) is full of clamors and incombrances, is trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the maſter, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times miniſters diſcontent to the gueſts: So populous courts are euer ſo interlarded with ſeruile, illiberall, thraſonicall,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17391:29"/> intruding and vnprofitable ſpirits, that for their owne ends haunts the Court, and (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though maintained with great charge) are euer ſubiect to quarrelling, wrangling, enuy, and diſcontentment, thereby enforcing Princes to leaue their kingly Soueraignty,<note place="margin">In infinita aulicorum multitudin ſunt Verſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploratores, qui Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras aularu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutiunt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia quae nouerint produnt. Petrar. dial. 22.</note> and become painefull ſpectatours, diligent mediators ouer them, whom they ought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Secondly, where there be many followers, the moſt ſecret affayres of Kings are (by cunning of corrupt flatterers, ſpies, and intelligenciers) expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon the rockes of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, and parat-like tongues of the fame ſpreading vulgar. Thirdly, many attendants (by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17391:30"/> the prodigall exhauſting of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes) ſo diſables Princes, that (without emptying their coffers, and impayring the publike good) they can neuer ſatiat the waſte and inexpleble bellies of all ſuch followers. Fourthly,<note place="margin">Ariſt. 5. ex dione Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio Val. max. lib. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Paucos ſeruos bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere difficile, plurimos impoſsibile est:</hi> As it is difficill to gouerne few well; ſo it is impoſſible to keepe many within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct of loyalty and obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. li. 2. fol. 70.</note>To ſhut vp all, the kingly ſtructure of Court, ought to be a patterne of vertues, is builded vpon the exemplary vertues of Princes, ſtrengthened and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden by the faithfull aduice of honourable counſellours; preſerued &amp; garniſhed by true
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17391:30"/> hearted ſubiects, and dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes: is ruined or defaccd by ſuch of thoſe, as make other vſe of their places, then that to which they were ordained<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Horace</hi> thus complaineth.<note place="margin">Orat. 1. Epiſt. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Pernicies, &amp; tempeſtas, barathru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> macelli</l>
                  <l>Nos numerus ſumus, &amp; fruges conſumere nati,</l>
                  <l>Sponſi Penelopes, nebulones alcinio<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>In cute curanda plus aequo operata iuue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus,</l>
                  <l>Cui pulchru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuit, in medios dormire dies, &amp;</l>
                  <l>Ad ſtrepidu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> citharae ceſſatum ducere cura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. IIII.</hi> What generall obſeruations the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and quiet gouernment of a Prince requireth.</head>
               <p>THeſe bee the chiefe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations that are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the right tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17391:31"/> of the actions of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:<note place="margin">Greg. apud Iob.</note> and attaining to a wiſhed calme amidſt the tempeſtuous ſeas, wherein they daily ſaile;</p>
               <p>Firſt, that their deſires be conſonant to reaſon, then which there is nothing that more beſeemes the dignity of Kings.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cic. 1. offic.</note>Secondly, that they wiſely eſtimate, the weight of matters in hand, leſt more or leſſe care be taken then is needfull.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that iudiciouſly they moderate thoſe things which doe belong to the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or indignity of affaires, neither comming ſhort, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding a Princely <hi>decorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, that they bee cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious in ſuffering: free hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17391:31"/> in giuing: thankfull in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding: mercifull in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and (ſetting aſide their priuate reſpects) referre all to the publike good:<note place="margin">Plato. de rep.</note> 
                  <hi>Vt tutela ſic procuratio reipublicae, ad vtilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eorum qui comiſsi ſunt, non ad eorum quibus comiſſa eſt, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, that Princes manure the whole body of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, by the equall diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of iuſtice, leſt by labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to make one part too fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, they leaue other parts barren: <hi>Totum corpus reipublicae cura, ne dum partem aliquam tuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris reliquas deſeras.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, Princes are to make vſe of the worthy counſell, that the Philoſopher did giue to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17391:32"/> 
                  <hi>Candicius</hi> the Theban: which was,<note place="margin">Epiſt. in ad. Eand. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 9.</note> that men of mature age, grauity, &amp; vpright iudgement, might bee his Deligates and helpers: that yong men might goe to the warres, or be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vertuouſly imployed. That women might keepe within doores: for (ſaid hee) if old men ſit by the fire: yong men be giuen to idleneſſe; and women goe about mens af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, the Common-wealth ſhall neuer be without danger, neyther thy perſon without paine. <hi>Principis est, pro ſalute Reipublicae &amp; noua excogitare, &amp; antiqua reſtituere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:17391:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. V.</hi> By what meanes the generous mindes of Princes are knowne.</head>
               <p>ALthough <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, <hi>Cor regis non perſcrutabile ſicut alitudo Coeli &amp; incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibile,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>ſicut profundtas ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae:</hi> Yet as the powerfull pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of heauen, and the fruites of the earth worketh vpon, &amp; nouriſheth inferiour bodies; ſo be there many heauenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences &amp; ſignes whereby the generous mindes of Princes are made knowne to their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: ſome whereof I will ſhortly touch.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the true generous
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17391:33"/> minde, of Princes, is knowen by their due reſpect to the Lawes of their Maker and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme King:<note place="margin">Salomon pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tit a deo ſapientiam ad regendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> populum dei, cui de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Cor ſapiens &amp; intelligens 3. Reg. 15.</note> with <hi>Salomon</hi> they are earneſt with God, that their chiefe wiſedome may be in his obedience, their delight in his commandements, that in their owne time iuſtice and peace may flouriſh, and that their poſterity after them may bee worthy to ſit in the chayre of of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the minde of true borne Princes,<note place="margin">Senec. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 15.</note> is not capable of baſe and ſordid actions; but is delighted in high and rare deſignes:<note place="margin">Senec. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note> for as the flame of fire (whoſe nature is to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend) cannot be depreſſed: So the minde of ſuch Princes, the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17391:33"/> more noble,<note place="margin">Macrob: lib. 2. cap. 4. Alezander nihil animo niſi grande concepit. Senec. de benef. li. 2.</note> the more inclined to Princely heroicke actions; euer contemnes thoſe things, which the vulgar holdes moſt deare. <hi>Principis animus quo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementior, eo nobilior &amp; actuoſior est; num foelix qui ad meliora hunc impetum dedit, &amp; extra ius ditionemque fortunae ſe profuſit; Contemptor eorum quae vulgus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miratur:</hi> Their care is to bee approoued of the good,<note place="margin">Eraſ. inſtit. Princ.</note> ſuch they preferre, ſuch are their counſellours, ſuch are alwayes about them; they are neuer (tyrant-like) cruel, nor vindic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue; nothing offends them more then the ſpoyle of vniuſt officers or corrupt iudges. <hi>Peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cennius imperator Conſiliarijs ſuis ne vel aliquam onerandi pauperes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17391:34"/> occaſionem haberet, addidit ſalla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, dicens, iudicem ac officiarium nec dare debere nec accipere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>og. Laert.</note>Thirdly, ſuch Princes ſuffer not good men, baſely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute themſelues, or ſeruily demand iuſtice; but are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly inclined to giue acceſſe and hearing. <hi>Aristippus,</hi> being reprooued by his friend, for ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo long at the feet of <hi>Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius;</hi> anſwered: I am not in the fault, but <hi>Dioniſius</hi> that hath cares in his feet.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l de opt. ſtat. Baptiſt. Fulg. lib. 4. Cic. ad Brut.</note>This Princely minde is euer giuen to follow the workes of light, as charitie, peace, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, goodneſſe and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; is wholly addicted to ſhun vices and follow vertue; wherin (euer keeping a golden
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17391:34"/> meane) they are meeke and mercifull; but ſo as by lenity they nouriſh not the vices of their people: ſeuere, not incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to tyranny, but in repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing iniuries, &amp; terifying others fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offering them.<note place="margin">Beroal. de opt. Stat.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui veterom fert iniuriam, inuitat nouam, ſi quis primus laeſerat debitas dediſſet penas, caeteri ab iniuria temper aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Chilon</hi> of <hi>Lacedemon</hi> adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Princes ſo to moderate their actions, as they be neither fearefull to their inferiours, or contemned of their equalls; the one ſauours of tyranny, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of puſillanimity.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the mind of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is giuen to true liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:<note place="margin">Prou. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Goodneſſe and truth vpholdes the throne of Kings,</hi> baſe aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryce
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17391:35"/> is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, chiefe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills, and moſt diſtant from true noble mindes.</p>
               <p>It was written vpon the tombe of queene <hi>Semiramis; Quiſquis Rex pecunijs eguerit, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perto monumento quantum volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in apo.</note> 
                  <hi>capiat:</hi> Couetous <hi>Darius</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken the citie, (expecting great ſtore of riches) cauſed the monument to bee opened, wherein he did finde nothing, but this following inſcription, vpon the other ſide of the ſtone, <hi>Ni vir malus eſſes, &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunia inexplebilis, haud mortuorum loculos moueres;</hi> wherof the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall is, that Princes are not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to ſearch,<note place="margin">Eraſ. 7. apo.</note> neither affect periſhing riches: <hi>Auarus Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps, facultates ſuas non poſsidet,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17391:35"/> ſed ipſum poſsident.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, the conſtant high minde of Princes, is not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with vnſetled reſolutions,<note place="margin">Eraſ. inſtit Princ.</note> but at all times is armed with true fortitude: they are ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puft vp with proſperitie neither deiected with aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, their maieſticall counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is euer one, at home or abroad.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Rebus aduerſis animoſus atque</l>
                  <l>Fortis appare, ſapienter idem</l>
                  <l>Contrahe vento nimium ſecundo</l>
                  <l>Turgida vela,</l>
               </q>
               <p>This Princely minde ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathiſes with ſuch as are of vpright heart, conſtant and true. <hi>Placeant regibus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>labia iuſta &amp; veraces diliguntur.</hi> The true friendſhip of <hi>Damon,</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17391:36"/> was ſo pleaſant to <hi>Dioniſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> (although a tyrant) that hee not only pardoned the offence of the one,<note place="margin">Val max cap 7.</note> but deſired to bee admitted into their friendſhip. A poore man exhibiting his bill fearefully to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> was by him thus checked, or rather comforted.<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rob. lib. 2 cap 9.</note> 
                  <hi>An putas te aſſem dare Elephanto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In one word, the kingly minds of good Princes, are free of all ſuch taints and violent paſſions, as praecipitates maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; are endowed with true patience, which is none of the leaſt Princely vertues; and was ſo eminent in <hi>Augustus Caeſar,</hi> that he could abide the byting ieſts of his meaneſt ſubiects. <hi>Conuitia ſi iraſcare agnita viden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17391:36"/> ſpreta exoleſount.</hi> When <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thocles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in apo.</note> the ſonne of a Potter (crowned with regall dignity) had beſieged a certaine towne, and entred the ſame, and had ſold ſuch for ſlaues, as had vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly depraued him; hee did meekely tell them, (if they did ſo any more) hee would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine to their maſters. <hi>Non ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines occidit, ſed ciuiliter illis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probarit &amp; intempestiuam maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam, &amp; ſeruitutem maledicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae praemium.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. VI.</hi> Of Nobilitie.</head>
               <p>WHere the ſeede of honour hath a true diſcent from nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17391:37"/> of anceſtors, a ground of vertue, ſpringing by noble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, continued with wiſdome, and maintained with care, a fruitfull harueſt, and plentifull winter cannot but follow: for as ſubiects are moſt eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to follow ancient nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; ſo oftimes vertue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes nobilitie of blood,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. fol. 97</note> and is the chiefe meanes whereby Princes attaine to the due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of neighboring friendes and ſubiects. Yet this nobility of anceſtors is not ſo to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed vpon, as if it could adde any thing (except ſeconded by goodneſſe) to the dignity of Princes:<note place="margin">Saluſt. in Iul.</note> For nobility is the act of time, and dieth with the Father, if the Son be not alike
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17391:37"/> vertuous.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Math.</note> 
                  <hi>Nobilitas cognatorum non valet, niſi fuerimus nos ipſi bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni;</hi> Nobility then by diſcent (without vertue) is rather an imaginary and vulgar opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then reall and true nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie:
<q>
                     <l>Nam genus &amp; proauos &amp; quae no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fecimus ipſi</l>
                     <l>Vix ea noſtra voco.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It is a ridiculous and oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue humour,<note place="margin">Franciſ. Petr. dial. 6.</note> to glory in the merit of others vertue; for certainly the ſplendour of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours, is the greateſt ſtaine, that can taint degenerating po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; the very name of a Prince, impoſeth a neceſſity of well doing vpon Kings; to this purpoſe <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth well, <hi>Ille clarus, ille ſublimis, ille tunc integram nobilitatem ſuam pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17391:38"/> qui dedignatur ſeruire vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs &amp; ab eis non vult ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. Iphicrates,</hi> the ſonne of a Shoo-maker (preferred to Emperiall dignitie) being taxed by degenerate <hi>Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi>) for the baſeneſſe of his birth;<note place="margin">Eraſ. apo.</note> anſwered, I am the beginner of my nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but thou the extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of thine. <hi>Caius Marius</hi> did glory in the multitude of wounds hee had receiued in defence of his Countrey; not in the glorious monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or images of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours.<note place="margin">Iuuenal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuuenall</hi> did hang <hi>Publius Plancus</hi> (who vſed to boaſt himſelfe diſcended from the noble family of <hi>Druſus</hi>) by the noſe; intimating to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17391:38"/> all ſucceeding proud gliſtering <hi>Thraſoes</hi> (that like Statues are good for nothing but to looke vpon, or talke of the nobility, powerfulneſſe, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and riches of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours) that they are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be laughed at. <hi>Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> gaue charge before his death, that no monument ſhould bee built for him: For, ſayd hee, if I haue liued vertuouſly, my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie ſhall not periſh;<note place="margin">Eraſ. 8. apo.</note> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needeth any Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gold, Marble, or Braſſe: but if I dye vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly I am worthie of none; they ſhal rather reuiue my infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my then illuſtrate my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Qui vere clarus videri velit ne
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17391:39"/> oſtentet ſculptas aut coloribus ad vmbratas imagines, in quibus ſi quid verae laudis eſt, id pectori de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur; ſed potius virtutis monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta moribus exprimat.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SETCIO. VII.</hi> Antidotes againſt the poyſoning of vaine glory, and ambitious thoughts, that intoxicates the mindes of young Princes.</head>
               <p>ALthough greatneſſe hath euer many ſoothers in vice,<note place="margin">Eraſ. inſtit. Prin.</note> perſons of baſe condition, attending and hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it round, with perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſelfe conceite; yet is earthly glory a deceiuable pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture drawne with falſe colours, blemiſhed with euery breath,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17391:39"/> the worke of fortune, blindly imparted to the good and bad. On the contrary, the true ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey of greatneſſe, is a diuine worke, and able to reſtraine the moſt powerful monarches from the dangerous pathes of pride, tyranny,<note place="margin">Plin. Pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> and ambitious aſpiring. <hi>Supra non extra homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Princeps, non minus hominem ſe quam hominibus praeeſſe cogitet.</hi> This ſerious examination hath the true originall from the due conſideration, what Princes are in their conception, in their birth, in their life, and what they ſhall be after death:<note place="margin">Is vitam ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua lance penſitauerit qui ſemper fragilitatis humanae memor fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit. Hiron. in Math.</note> They are (as all men) concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſinne, borne naked, leſſe able then many more baſe creatures to take food, or helpe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17391:40"/> themſelues: they liue not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expoſed to humane diſeaſes and worldly cares, to which priuate men are ſubiect; but to many miſeries, from which the vulgar are exempted: after their death, they muſt bee food for wormes, and againe, (with all men) aſſume thoſe ſame bodies, and in them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a correſpondent reward, as they haue vſed their talent.</p>
               <p>Princes are to conſider, that all goodneſſe is the free gift of God;<note place="margin">Eraſ. in Mil. Chriſt.</note> freely beſtowed vpon them, for the weale of them and their ſubiects: but euery diſordered affection, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the corruption of nature, and enclineth vnto ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny: They ought to thinke
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17391:40"/> that their Vicegerency from God is their greateſt glory;<note place="margin">Fortunam tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> O Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps, preſſis manibus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. lubrica, eſt, nec in vito teneri poteſt; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone foelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati fraenos, facilius eam Reges. Curt. lib. 8.</note> that they are to exerciſe it but for a ſhort time: that although they bee entituled to all ſuch glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous titles as may exalt ſwelling pride; yet who knoweth but to morrow they may bee (where all kings before them are) the foode of Serpents and Worms. All fleſh is but Duſt and Aſhes, and therefore hath no cauſe to be prowd: It is like to the graſſe of the field, this day greene to morrow withered. Brittle is the greatneſſe that fadeth in a moment.<note place="margin">An ignoras magnos ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores diu creſcere, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na hora extirpari idem Curt.</note> If Princes had the wiſedome of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Abſolon,</hi> the ſtrength of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the riches of <hi>Craeſus,</hi> and the long life of <hi>Methuſalem,</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:17391:41"/> what ſhall all theſe fayling va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities auayle, except by a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous raigne in this ſhort king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of cares,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de natu. &amp; gra.</note> they ſo dignifie themſelues, that they may bee entailed to an euerlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Ioyes. Where be the glorious ſhewes of moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Monarchs? whoſe pride builded high aſpiring <hi>Babylon,</hi> whoſe ambition one world could not containe?<note place="margin">Ambroſ. in exam.</note> where bee the inuincible Emperours that did ouer-rule the world, the horſe, out-landiſh attire, nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of attendants, leaders of troops and al other falſe pleaſures that did atttend vpon pride? are they not turnd into aſhes? doth not the leaſt puſh of death make ſhepheards and kings e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual?
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17391:41"/> was not the birth of thoſe great Cedars of <hi>Lebanon</hi> weake, their life inconſtant, their death putrifaction? looke into their ſepulchers, and diſcerne who was a king, who was a ſubiect, who was rich, who was poore; finde out (if thou canſt) the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor from the conquered, the ſtrong from the weake, the beautifull from the deformed: or trye ſome cauſe of humane arrogancie,<note place="margin">Agap. ad Iuſtin.</note> thou ſhalt finde pride and ambition neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the counſels of the wiſe, nor bodies of the dead. <hi>Factus es princeps in terra, ne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res te ortum ex terra ex puluere ad ſolium aſcendere, atque in eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem puluerem diſcendere neceſſe eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:17391:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SETCIO. VIII.</hi> How Princes ought to moderate their power.</head>
               <p>THe due calling to mind that a Prince is <hi>homo</hi> (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which all worldly miſeries and vanities are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended) ought to bridle his power, and the conſideration that he is <hi>Deus,</hi> or, <hi>vice Dei,</hi> Gods vicegerent, ought to curb his will.<note place="margin">Memento ait mihi omnia in omnes lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Suet.</note> 
                  <hi>Meminerit princeps non ſolum quantum ſit tibi comiſſum ſed quatenus fit permiſſum. Quod libetli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet,</hi> is the <hi>dictum</hi> of a Tyrant, &amp; the right mixture of contraries, is the true temper of gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nothing being more
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17391:42"/> hurtfull to authoritie, then vntimely interchange of preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and relaxing power. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie temperandum ſceptrum &amp; laxandae aut addendae imperij il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae habenae.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in apo.</note> The arrogant pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption that all thinges are lawfull,<note place="margin">Diog. lat.</note> is the poyſon which once drunke, makes Kings abuſe their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and encline to licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and tyranny. <hi>Antigonus</hi> did ſeuerely checke one of his Courtiours who did ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt that all things were lawfull for Kings. Not ſo (by <hi>Iupiter</hi>) ſayd he, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to tyrannous and barbarous Kings; but to mee nothing is lawfull but that which is honeſt and iuſt: authority is not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17391:43"/> giuen to be the ſupplement of vice or the protection of tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; but to be the defence of vertue, and patterne of iuſtice. <hi>A recte agendo vocati Reges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. 11. Moral.</note> 
                  <hi>quod recte agendo regale nomen obtinent amittunt peccando.</hi> The right tempering of authority is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to dull the edge of the imperiall ſword with leuitie and mercy,<note place="margin">Eraſm. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. prin.</note> which makes ſubiects more carefull to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. Other times kingly au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is reſtrained from things that are lawfull to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 1. fol. 2.</note> errors in priuate perſons are vices and blemiſhes in kings.</p>
               <p>Finally, the affecting of iuſtice, the floriſhing eſtate of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, the modeſt life of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17391:43"/> ſubiects, contempt and hatred of tyrrannous liberty,<note place="margin">Argumentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recte guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati regni, ſi ſubdito; videas locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletiores ac vehementer modeſtos cura princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis reditor. Rein. lor. Iſocrat. ad Nicol.</note> volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and ſuperfluous aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, wicked followers, and blindfolded ignorance is the true extent of authoritie. <hi>Ne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimum inducas tuum alios debere honeſte vitam agere, regibus immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſte viuendi relicta licentia, ſed ea ſis temperantia vt exemplum recte viuendi alijs conſtituas, compertum habens ſubditorum mores prorſus ad ſimilitudinem principis componi.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:17391:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. IX.</hi> Whoſe image good and bad Princes repreſent, by what Epithetes they are knowne, and of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall actions.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eraſ: 3. Apo</note>GOod Princes repreſent the image of God,<note place="margin">Vt deorum cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſint op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time natura propriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, benefacere omnibus, nocere ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini: ita princeps ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutaris quo nihil deo proprius, omnibus prodeſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſtude incomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Plato. de repub. ex Iulio pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luc.</note> whoſe vicegerents they are; him they do imitate (to whom it is eſſentiall to be goodneſſe it ſelfe) in doing good to all, and incommodating none. They do not (like wolues) prey vpon their people, but cheriſh and protect them: they puniſh but ſeldom, &amp; then are vnwillingly drawne to it; and therfore iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch Princes are intituled to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17391:44"/> the names, of fathers, religious, meeke, gentle, prouident, iuſt, humane, magnanimous, free, liberall, contemners of riches, commanding and ouerruling their affections, of ſound iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wiſe in counſell, ſober,<note place="margin">Demoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apud Stob.</note> vpright, firme, full of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, princely Maieſtie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, carefull watchers ouer their people, ready to do good, ſlow to reuenge, ſure, conſtant, enclined to iuſtice, eaſie to giue acceſſe, courteous in ſpeech, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the obedient, louers, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curers, keepers of peace, yet friends to ſoldiers, and (if need be) can be both kings and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains. Such Princes are born to the good, doe liue with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor, and die with the regrate of all men.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:17391:45"/>
               <p>On the contrary, if <hi>Apelles</hi> ſhould delineate a tyrrannous wicked Prince, he could not do drawit otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of the Prince of darkenes, a monſtrous miſhapen creature, an armed dragon with many eyes,<note place="margin">Ex Eraſm.</note> more teeth, ſharpe clawes, inſatiable belly, crammed with humane blood, euery way fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and offenſiue to all, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to good men, abuſing his power, to the preiudice of the Commonwealth. Such a Prince was <hi>Nero,</hi> ſuch was <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula,</hi> ſuch was <hi>Heliogabulus</hi> and many others, whoſe birth and life were plagues to the world, and did iuſtly merite the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetes of tyrants, vngodly, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, ſauage, violent, auaritious,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17391:45"/> deuourers of their people: prowd,<note place="margin">Tamerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Scitha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum rex ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus, quid tantum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitiae indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geret, toruo vultu reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe fertur, anme homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eſſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, an non potius dei iram ad ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciem in terris agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Sabel. de ir.</note> difficill in giuing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, vncourteous, irefull, terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſlaues to luſts, intemperate, inconſiderate, inhumane, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, light, vnconſtant, incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, contumelious, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of warre, haters and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of peace, borne to be the (<hi>Tamerlan</hi> like) ſcourges of the world, reigning with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, and dying with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of all good men.</p>
               <p>As the Epithetes of good &amp; wicked Princes are, ſo are their actions different,<note place="margin">Saluſt. in Caril.</note> the one ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances &amp; Confirmes the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, preferres it to al pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate reſpects: tyrrany aymes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together at their owne priuate ends, neglects the publicke
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17391:46"/> good; either approuing the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable oath of Oliarchy, <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem odio perſequemur &amp; pro viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li adnitemur vt illi ſit male,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt. pol. 5.</note> Or with arrogant <hi>Xerxes</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulting vpon affaiers rather to ſhewe their power; then for the weal of their ſubiects:<note place="margin">Eraſ. apo. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne viderer meo conſilio agreſſus contraxi, vos, interim mementote mihi pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum magis quam ſuadendum.</hi> In a word the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt good and bad Princes, is ſuch, as is betwixt louing fathers, and rigorous Maſters; the one affectes the weale; and health of their children, the other the gaine they make by their ſlaues. Good Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces commands things that are profitable to the State, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17391:46"/> ſuch as are pleaſant, to their owne humours. It is the glory of good kings to follow vertue, of tyrants to embrace vice, of good Princes to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the loue of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,<note place="margin">Iſocrat de bell. fugien.</note> of tyrants by the ſtrength of wals, and multitude of guards.</p>
               <p>Finally, the frame, the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and qualities of good Princes and Tyrants are ſo vnlike and different as God and <hi>Belial,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicero of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. 3.</note> Light and Darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, White and Blacke: ſo that there is no bleſſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen giuen to man more profitable then religious wiſe Princes, no greater curſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue hell, more pernitious then Tyrants, placed in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:17391:47"/>
               <p>I haue inſiſted this farre vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theſe diuers attributes and differences, that thereby good Princes may bee incited (at fit times) to peruſe the Annals &amp; Hiſtories of former times, wherein they may reape much fruite,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. li. 2. fol 93. Eccleſ. 1.</note> by conferring things paſt with things preſent, <hi>Nihil nouum ſub ſole,</hi> there they ſhall finde the true proportion, liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly colours, and bright ſhining luſtre of vertue, and the vgly deformed ſhape of black neuer dying infamy. <hi>Principibus bonis nihil melius, contra nihil peius tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannis qui eiuſ modi belluae ſunt, vt non alia ſub ſole portenta ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noxia, neque magis omnibus inuiſa.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:17391:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. X.</hi> By what meanes a Prince may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelfe in his kingdome and obtaine the loue of his ſubiects.</head>
               <p>AS wiſedome (which is the brightneſſe of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting light, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled myrror of the Maieſty of God, and image of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) is the ſure ground of the ſtately pillar of gouernement:<note place="margin">Prudentiae ad omnis res huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos vſus, ſed ad impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me quod ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ea non ſolum infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſit ſed nullum. Lip. lib. 3.1.</note> ſo is the fauour of ſubiects, the maintainer of ſo glorious buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and the kingdomes that are gouerned by the vertue of Princes, and loue of ſubiects are moſt quiet and firme. The moſt vndomeable beaſts are
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17391:48"/> made more eaſily mylde, by gentle familiar vſage, then by roughneſſe or ſtripes; and the loue of Subiects (without which Princes can neuer be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured) is ſooner conciliate, by beneuolence, then by vnbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled authoritie and crueltie.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are the meeke in heart for they ſhall poſſeſſe the inheritance of the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall be delighted in the multitude of peace,</hi> was not written in vayn, but for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of kings, &amp; eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of kingdomes, by the fruits of wiſdome, not by the effects of Phalariſme.<note place="margin">Diog. lib. 2</note> 
                  <hi>Ciuibus placere ſtude, habet id multum gratiae,</hi> was the worthy ſentence of <hi>Bias:</hi> for (ſayd he) if Princes ſhould deſire to equall or exceed <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crops</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:17391:48"/> in nobilitie, <hi>Policrates</hi> in happineſſe, <hi>Craeſus</hi> in riches, <hi>Xerxes</hi> in armies, <hi>Caeſar</hi> in victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and <hi>Pompey</hi> in tryumphs:<note place="margin">Eraſ. in paneg. ad Philip.</note> no helpes can ſo auayle them as the vnited and true loue of ſubiects, which is the impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſtrength, and neuer emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed treaſure of kings;<note place="margin">Claudiam in uonſul. honor.</note> 
                  <hi>Non ſic excubiae, non circumſtantia pila quam tutator amor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Empire of kings ouer their ſubiectes is compared to the command of fathers ouer their children, or maſters ouer their ſchollers:<note place="margin">Senec. de Clement.</note> as he is no lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing father that beates his ſon for euery ſlight fault, and no leſſe cruell maſter that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his ſcholler for the natural defects of his ſight or hearing.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17391:49"/> So many rigorous precede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of puniſhment are no leſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull to a king,<note place="margin">Ferina eſt rabies ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere &amp; vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neribus, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecto homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in Silue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre animal tranſire. Rhen. Lor.</note> then many buryals to a Phyſition. <hi>Seueritas amittit aſsiduitate authoritatem.</hi> The more remiſſe kings go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, the more they are hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, loued, and obeyed: no ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue becommeth them better then clemency; neither more ſurely bindeth the hearts of people. What is more ioyfull then to rule with the applauſe of men? Who dares imagine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harme againſt that Prince that is meeke and mercifull, vnder whoſe ſheltring wings Iuſtice, Peace, Security and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours flouriſh?<note place="margin">Eccl. 10:15. Luke 1.52. &amp; 14.11.</note> Meekeneſſe and Mercy eſtabliſheth the throne of a king: Pride and Crueltie
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17391:49"/> ouerthrowes the ſeate of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.<note place="margin">Pſalm.</note> 
                  <hi>Sedes diuum ſuperborum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruxit D us, &amp; ſedere fecit mites pro eis.</hi> The houſe of the wicked ſhall be ouerturned, but the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of the godly ſhall flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Let the ſhort raigne and tragicall end of <hi>Dionyſius, Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula, Vitellius,</hi> and many others, (whoſe tyrrannous life haſtned their wiſhed, yet immature death) confirme that no tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is of long continuance, that ſuch are much deceiued that dreames ſtabilitie,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.10. &amp; 18.19. 1. Sam. 2.7.8. Thales Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſius inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roganti. quid difficile ſene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inquit, videre tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. ap. Stob. Cic. 5. offic.</note> or ſecuritie to Princes without goodneſſe. <hi>Exiſtimatum demum te tuto regnare cum volentibus imperas:</hi> the Prince that wants the fauour of his people hath loſt his chief guard and that Prince that is fearfull
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17391:50"/> to many, muſt of neceſſitie be afrayd of many.<note place="margin">Non ſunt adamantina imperij vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula quae Dionyſius Tyrannus dictitabat. ex Plut.</note> 
                  <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant excruciated with this feare, did make choice to ſuffer the paine of ſingeing the haire of his beard with hot fire, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit his conſcious life to the truſt of a Barbors raſor.<note place="margin">Acl. Soart.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexander Pharees</hi> neuer entered his Queenes chamber before diligent ſeareh was made, that no priuate weapon were hidden in it: yet (if wee will wade into the ſhallow brookes of the heathen) wee ſhall find that the liues of theſe and thouſands more of heathen Princes was tyrannous, &amp; their death miſerable: but we Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians learne our leſſon from our maker. <hi>Mihi vindicta, vltio
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:17391:50"/> mea eſt, ego retribuam,</hi> ſayth the Lord.<note place="margin">Deut. 32. Rom. 11.</note> We muſt thinke our ſins the iuſt cauſe of our afflictions, and that God ſometimes ſends wicked kings to the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of wicked people;<note place="margin">Dabo reges in ſurore meo. Oſee. 13. Qui malum rectore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur Deum non accuſet, quia ſui fuit meriti, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſi recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſubiacere ditioni. Gre. ſup. Iob.</note> and as God giueth them for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne: ſo muſt Gods people onely by repentance and amendment, ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to his pleaſure, in whoſe hands are the hearts of kings. It is not lawfull to think an ill thought of kings, far leſſe to lay hands on the Lords annointed.<note place="margin">Poteſtas omni, ſiue bona, ſiue mala, à deo eſt, Itaque poteſt tibus ſiue bonis, ſiue malis honortribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endus eſt. Augu. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Manichae</note> Let not the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d but the hart of a traitor be acurſed, let his fleſh be carnage to the foules of the aire, his bowels ſacrificed to the hangma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; his memory eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon the tables of blacke
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17391:51"/> infamy. But to come to my purpoſe;<note place="margin">Rein. Lor.</note> Iſay a Prince hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gates to receiue the fauour &amp; loue of his people, amongſt which I ſhall ſhortly poynt at foure.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe pride is hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to all men;<note place="margin">Eccleſ 10.7. Cic. de or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Senec. Epiſt. 18.</note> Princes ſhall ſhun the enuy that comes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, if they do not boaſt of their high fortune, power, riches, or what elſe is more deare vnto them, accounting no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of them,<note place="margin">Plut. in. Pol.</note> then as of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine goods of fortune; and that they can auayle them no further, but according to the good or bad vſe of them.<note place="margin">Potentiae, in inſuetudo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ungatur, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ob.</note> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie and humility are no leſſe eminent in Princes then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and are the actractiue A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damants
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17391:51"/> that drawes the loue of ſubiects to their king:<note place="margin">Greg. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. 17.</note> we do ſee the motion of the Sunne is moſt ſlow, when it is higheſt in his Zodiake: So the more high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greatneſſe is promoted, it ought to be the more ſetled &amp; calme. <hi>Salomon</hi> (to this purpoſe) giueth aduice; <hi>My ſonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>in all thy workes embrace meekneſſe, and thou ſhalt be loued aboue the glory of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, there be two things peculiar vnto kings, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues iuſt and lawfull, whereof the timely or vntimely preſſing auayleth much to conciliate the loue or diſlike of ſubiectes. The firſt is, impoſing and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſubſidies for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke good, and maintaining of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17391:52"/> the great charges of kings: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be as due to them from their people, as iuſtice, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency,<note place="margin">Rom 13.6. Mat. 22.21. Mar. 12.17. Luc. 20.</note> and protection is from Princes to ſubiects: yet are they to bee impoſed as ſeldome as may be,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. de fol. 99.</note> and onely when the weighty affaires of Princes and ſtate ſo requires. <hi>Ieroboam</hi> by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing heuy burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; exactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpon his people was puniſhed by the cutting off ten tribes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his kingdomes;<note place="margin">Pater meus cecedit vos flagellis ego cedam vos ſcorpioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. 1. Reg. 11.</note> wherby is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated to future poſterity that altaints of (tirantlike) oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; baſe auarice (euer liable to conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt) are fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kings far to be remoued.<note place="margin">Phil. Com. 10.</note> The other obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is in making of new, or refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ancient lawes or cuſtoms crept into abuſe,<note place="margin">Xen. in Cir.</note> or remouing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17391:52"/> ſuch as at the inſtitution were profitable, yet for the preſent time, are either hurtfull or not neceſſary:<note place="margin">Legis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus non recreatae marceſcunt. Plat. de leg.</note> in all which Princes are to keep ſuch te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate, mean, as their proceedings may bee warranted by the generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the moſt wiſe and beſt ſort of ſubiects,<note place="margin">Areſt. 5. pol</note> and freed from all ſuſpition of particular ends or raſhnes. <hi>Nouum omne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dion. 22. Thuc. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; quod incognitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, ſuſpectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt.</hi> The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name of nouelty is oft times more offenſiue to ſtate, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the benefit that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes therby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. For this cauſe Princes ſomtimes tolerate ſuch things as without the preiudice of the Common-wealth, and their royall dignity, may be ſuffered: otherwiſe things that haue had long continuace are by little
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17391:53"/> and little to bee reformed. <hi>Si quid eiuſmodi erit vt ferri poſsit aut tollerare conueniet, aut commode ad meliorem vſum deflectere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, if Princes ſhewe themſelues affable and exorable not vindictiue and ſeuere in the rigorous execution of lawes for euery light offence; they ſhall much obliege the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and obedience of their ſubiects: for as impunity beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth contempt of lawes: ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent puniſhment ingenerates hatred, ſenſleſſe ſtupiditie, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, &amp; contentious repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancie. <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> was ſo familiar with his ſubiects that hee did louingly name ſome father, ſome ſon, according to their dignities &amp; qualities. This
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17391:53"/> Princely familiarity made him ſo beloued,<note place="margin">Quae hoc tempore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus bona ob nullam aliam cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam adepti ſumus, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ob praeſtita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obedientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principi. Pith. apud Stob. Saluſt. ad Caeſar.</note> in his life time &amp; at his death ſo condoled with the briniſh teares of his ſorrowfull ſubiects, that it is recorded to his neuer dying prayſe: <hi>Cum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremum diem clauſiſset, tantus illius amor, eo die regij funeris claruit, vt nemo illum non plangendum cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, becauſe animaduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the liues and manners of people, euen in matters whereof penall lawes takes lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no hold, is powerfull in conquering the loue of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and to eterniſe the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of Princes with true glory. They are carefully to curbe blaſphemy, luxury,<note place="margin">Iuuenal. Sa. 6. Tacit. 12 Anal.</note> Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, prodigality, idleneſſe, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17391:54"/> ſuch other vices as are (in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and ſorts people) repugnant to godlines or good manners. <hi>Prauas artes malaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> libidines ab iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentute prohibebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, a ſenibus eas vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptates quas eorum aetas ſine dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>core non attingit, ab vniuerſa plebe otium.</hi> They are carefully to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue their people from blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucking vſury,<note place="margin">Vbi diuitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cupido inuaſit, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, neque bonae artes ſatis pollent itaque meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to princeps pecuniaeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium tollet, aut quo ad res feret mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuet, atque alligabit il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud vtbibus vetus, faene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre malum. Ariſt. pol. 7. Tacit. 6. anal Plin. paneg.</note> &amp; exorbitant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, ſo oft accurſed in Gods ſacred word, &amp; accounted (with traitrous <hi>Iudas</hi> his 30. peeces) the price of blood. Laſtly, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to forbid all ſumptuous riot and prodigally profuſed charges in building: <hi>ne nimis ſtruant, aut inſtruant:</hi> in houſe keeping or dyet: <hi>ne luxus menſae profuſis ſumptibus exerciatur.</hi> That in clothing a deeent modeſtie a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17391:54"/> all degrees, ſexes and ages be kept, <hi>Ne veſtis promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cua viris &amp; faeminis, nobilibus, &amp; plebeijs, nam conuiuiorum luxuria &amp; veſtium, aegrae ciuitatis indicia ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SETCIO. XI.</hi> Princes ought be eaſie in giuing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and ready to hoare the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the oppreſſed and poore</head>
               <p>THe hearing of the cauſes of ſubiectes the iuſt bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing &amp; determining them,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. fol. 35. Diues ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis, non exauditur, quia rogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>audiuit in terris. Auguſt. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de diuit.</note> is the chiefe part of a kings office. <hi>Mercy and truth eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth the throne of kings, but hee that regardeth not the crye of the poore, ſhall cry and not be heard.</hi> To this purpoſe S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> aduiſeth
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:17391:55"/> Princes to be eaſie in giuing of acceſſe, &amp; hearing of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of all men, <hi>Quia inaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti atque indefenſi tanquam inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes pereunt. Moſes</hi> did heare the people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> morning til eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.<note place="margin">Exod. 18.19</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> did wiſely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the cauſe of a poore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute harlot.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 3.17</note> His father <hi>Dauid</hi> did delight in vpright iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">Suet. in Caeſ</note> But to leaue this diuine Ocean, and come to the ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low riuers of the heathen; <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauius Auguſtus</hi> did ſometimes ſpend whole dayes, and beſt part of the night in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of iuſtice. <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> did the like,<note place="margin">Acl. Spart.</note> and did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely puniſh ſuch ſubordinate Magiſtrates as were found ſlacke in their office. <hi>Methrida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:17391:55"/> did miniſter iuſtice in 21. languages to the people vnder his Empire. <hi>Imperatorem ſtantem mori oportet, hoc eſt in cauſis audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endis, rebuſque componendis ſtrenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; erectum vſque at extremum vitae momentum oportere.</hi> As the people do much magnifie and honor ſuch Princes as willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe heare their complaynts and determine their cauſes: So doe they contemptuouſly (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſecretly) hate thoſe, whoſe pryde, tyranous anſwers and difficill acceſſe, do vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily challenge the name of Empyre. Amongſt theſe was <hi>Demetrius</hi> who (after two years attendance) did returne the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian</hi> Embaſſadours without anſwer; and at another time
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:17391:56"/> did publiſh,<note place="margin">Mulier quae dam Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem rogauit vtſe audiret cui ille, otiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mihi non eſt, illade in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de clamans ait, noli er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go imperar. Ex Plut.</note> that vpon a certain day enſuing hee would heare the complaints of ſuch as were greeued: but when at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed time hee had liberally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued their petitions, hee did throw them all into the riuer: <hi>Axis,</hi> by which careleſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of himſelf he did migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily exaſperate and alieanate the hearts of his people. Good prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to direct their courſe (by the compaſſe of a good conſcience) a quite contrary way they are not to throw the groanes of their ſubiects in the riuers of obliuion,<note place="margin">Beroal. de opt. ſtatu.</note> neither in the all conſuming fire of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, or commit them to ſuch perſons who endeares more their owne priuate gaine
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:17391:56"/> then the publicke good: but are to appoynt them ſeaſons of hearing, and returne them lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and Princely anſwers.<note place="margin">Eraſm. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. princ.</note> If ſometime multiplicity of ſtate affaires withdraw them, they are carefull that their deligates neither careleſly deferre hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, nor coueteouſly exact vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuitors.<note place="margin">Perſarum reges, domi abditi vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exigebant, omniaque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regni nego tia rejicie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliarios ac officiarios. Eraſ. ee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. princ. Senec. de clement.</note> The obſcure life of the <hi>Perſian</hi> kings, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting all the affaires of ſtate, to ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate perſons, was neuer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of the wiſe, and euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to their diſcredit. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (to truſſe vp al) it is the glory of kings to imitate thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Princes that did equally adminiſter iuſtice, giue eaſie acceſſe, louing anſwers, ſtrengthening the weake,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:17391:57"/> and rewarding the vertuous, and puniſhing the wicked, and were carefull that their Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates did ſecond their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the truſt committed to them-This kingly function ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſheth the hearts of ſubiects to their Prince, and freeth Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the propheticall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Pricincipes tui infideles, ſocij farum, omnes diligunt munera, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur retributiones: Pupillo non indicant &amp; cauſa viduae non ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur ad illos.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:17391:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XII.</hi> Of the neceſsitie of Princes know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the affaires of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and preſence (ſo farre as is poſsible) in the adminiſtration of Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>THe ancient Hierogli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicke deſcription of Princes,<note place="margin">Deus in coelo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, omnia ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gore ſuo per. luſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. ita in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem, cuius oculorum perſpicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas luceret in populo, cunctiſque perſpiceret colocauit. Iuſt. Caeſar Homer. Illiad.</note> (picturing ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with eyes) did myſtically containe the moſt neceſſarie parts of the office of kings; whoſe quicke ſeeing eyes muſt ſee into the moſt darke corners of their dominions. The Sunne is the eye of the world, but ſees not, but the king giues light to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:17391:58"/> his ſubiects: muſt with Eagles eyes looke vpon all ſubiects, pry into all Courts, obſerue Iudges and Officers; leſt the golden cloaked reaſons of the rich or corrupted ouerſway the innocency of the poore. <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> are the keepers, or (as <hi>Homer</hi> calls them) ſhepheards of their people.<note place="margin">Studeat im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primis prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ac ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatum ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudines, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta; popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. Eraſm. de inſtit. princip.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne ſubditi a Deo optimo maximo ſibi concrediti a lupis rapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus deuorentur:</hi> They are exactly to know the true eſtate and peccant humours of their people; to which they may eaſily attaine, by Geography, Hiſtory, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent progreſſe, and ſure intelligence: by theſe they ſhall learne the ſcituation of their ſeuerall Countreys or
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:17391:58"/> Prouinces, the cuſtomes,<note place="margin">Princeps ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acutè quam ſerpens Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daurus cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere debet, quid in can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellarijs, quid in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſterijs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, an Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis iudicijs, iudicetur populus. Macrob. li. 2 Deligat princeps quoſda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel aulicorum, vel ſubdito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, non a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaros, ſed fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de charitate conſpicuos, quos clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulos regni terminos ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leget, expiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum &amp; perceptum omnes vel relaxationes vel agraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perij. Ariſt. Pol.</note> liues and manners of their people. It is written to the prayſe of King <hi>Ierion,</hi> that hee had many hands, more feete, and but one minde, by which hee gouerned his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: That many other wiſe Princes haue ſecretly employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch, of whoſe integritie and loue to the publicke good they were well aſſured, to take true information of the remiſneſſe or ſtrictneſſe of gouernement: in what eſtate publicke and priuate affaires did remaine: how the people were affected to obedience and vertuous liuing: whether Iudges, Magiſtrates and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers were enclined to Iuſtice
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:17391:59"/> and vpright dealing, to the publicke good, or their priuate gaine: that after true notice thereof,<note place="margin">Preſentia principis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit omnia iuſto ordine procedere Ariſt. Aeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſuch myſty cloudes as did ouer ſhadow their people, might (by the Sunſhine of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) be diſperſed. But although this ſecret enquirie by others is prayſe worthy, yet is the preſence of princes (ſo farre as is poſſible) of much more conſequence. <hi>Non tam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciter procedunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Si magna paruis licet componere, vt oculus Creſini fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſſimum agrum: ita principis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uam tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicam florentiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam reddit Agricol. in prouerb. Ger.</note> 
                  <hi>quae oculis agis alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quam quae oculo domini praeſente adminiſtrantur. Cajus Furius Creſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> being accuſed for the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing of ſorcery, in multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the encreaſe of a little field of corne, anſwered, <hi>Omnia inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta mea ruſtica in forum affero, venificia mea Quirites haec ſunt:</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:17391:59"/> Then layde hee open his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, his paines and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preſence,<note place="margin">Principe dormitante, ſuboriri ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulenti, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeratores auari, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actores in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſti, qui ſuis ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros ſubditos concutiunt exhauriunt &amp; perdunt. Rhein. Lor.</note> then which there is nothing more beſeeming Princes in their royall office, neither more profitable for ſubiects in the augmentation of their priuate gaine: for to what greater indignity or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt can Princes bee lyable then to cecity and ſenſleſſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piditie? by which they doe not feele the abuſes, whereby (vnder the vayle of their princely authority) the poore are oppreſſed, the ſweat and oft times the blood of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and weak is exhauſted, the poſſeſſions, houſes, fields, goods of widdowes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants (by theſe that in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:17391:60"/> and authority are powerfull) are either deceyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully purloyned, or violently bereft. By the ſtrickt obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation or careleſſe neglect of this princely ſuruay, many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous kingdomes haue flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, or beene vtterly ruinated: amongſt which I wil illuſtrate this poynt, by a ſhort view of the cauſes of the large domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, long continuance, and ſodaine ouerthrow of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Empire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Romani propter oculatiſsimam in publices functiones intentionem atque conſeruatas iuſtitiae leges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Val. Max. lib. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiſsimi atque optimi duces vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que gentium caelebrati ſunt; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores ac domini totius ferme ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum orbis floruerunt tantiſper
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:17391:60"/> dum Iuſtitiae ſtudium, atque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae in imperio ſuo non emarcue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt: at poſtquam ambitio, ſimul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, luxus, ac pecuniae libido, (quae generis humani certiſsimae peſtes) ingruerunt, ſtatim praepotens illud imperium, praeclara dignitas, atque gentis omnibus ſtupenda Populi Romani maieſtas, ad nihilum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacta corruit, in memorabile cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis mundi gubernatoribus exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:17391:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XIII.</hi> Of Lawes and Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>ALL humane lawes may bee reduced to a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold diuiſion, <hi>viz.</hi> to the lawes of nature,<note place="margin">Egip. de leg:</note> the lawes eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and to the ancient co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary lawes. That which the ancients did call the law of nature (as to do good and ſhun euill,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Ciuit. dei.</note> doe to others, as we wold others ſhould doe to vs) needes no great learning, becauſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon draweth men to the knowledge of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aul. Gel. lib. 5.</note>The lawes eſtabliſhed are ſuch as are preſcribed by Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17391:61"/> and Kings for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerntment of their people, and do conſiſt, partly in reaſon, partly in opinion.</p>
               <p>Cuſtomary lawes are ſuch, as by little and little,<note place="margin">Haelinand. lib. 7.</note> haue bin brought among people, and haue no other force, but in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well or ill obſerued. In ſhort, we call the law of nature that wbich reaſon commands; the lawe eſtabliſhed that which is written and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: cuſtomary Law that which hath long beene, and now is in vſe.</p>
               <p>Other ancient lawyers ſubdiuides lawes,<note place="margin">Gratian, lib. 3.</note> in lawes of nations, ciuill lawes, conſular lawes, publicke lawes, military lawes, Romane lawes, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:17391:62"/> lawes of Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>The law of nations is a law by all people generally obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:<note place="margin">Papinian. lib. 3.</note> (as to ſeize vpon that which hath no owner, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their countrey) it is called the law of nations, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all nations it hath bin generally receiued and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iuſtin. Cod: 4.</note>The ciuil law hath the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the right inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and proſecution of proceſſe: to aſſigne time, to anſwer, accuſe, proue, oppoſe, cite, alledge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, conclude, giue ſentence &amp; to execute it, to the end that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one might haue their due and be defended from wrong. Conſular law did enact what men of life Conſuls ſhould bee, what
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:17391:62"/> habit they ſhould haue, how they ſhould be accompanyed,<note place="margin">Trog. Pom. lib. 2.</note> where they ſhould aſſemble, of what affairs they ſhould treat, how long they ſhould ſit, and what goods they ſhould poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe.<note place="margin">Iuſt. lib. 22.</note> This law was peculiar onely to the Conſuls of <hi>Rome. Leges Quiritum</hi> were Roman lawes or priuiledges, proper to foure ſorts of noble, ancient, &amp; worthy Roman gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricijs, veteranis, militibus, &amp; Quiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus:</hi> al which names were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed according to the variety of time: by this law they were priuiledgd to ſit in their te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, not to be impriſoned for debt; &amp; if any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were ſeized by pouerty, to bee ſuſtained vpon the common good, to be liable
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:17391:63"/> onely to the Iudicatory of Rome, to bee free of taxes and ſubſidies, and to haue the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of diuers other priuiledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that none except the aboue named perſons enioyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lsges publicae</hi> were common ordinances or ſtatutes, that all the people did obſerue, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payring of Temples, common houſes,<note place="margin">Capitoll. lib. 3.</note> walls of citties, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of ſtreets, prouiding of things needfull to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vſe, gathering of taxes, impoſitions, and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Veget lib. 7</note>Lawes Militar were ſuch as were made by thoſe of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and experience, to whom the ordering of military affairs was committed, and do chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſt in denouncing war,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:17391:63"/> confirming peace, making ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntments, taking aſſurance, in paying of ſouldyers, ſetting of guards, watches and ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, making of trenches, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning of battels, in giuing the aſſault, making the retreat, redeeming priſoners, appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of tryumphs, and finally, in whatſoeuer did concerne the gouernment of military af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres.</p>
               <p>The lawes of Magiſtrates were lawes made by diuers Princes and Conſuls, and had their names fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the authors as <hi>Lex Caeſarea</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded gates to be open at time of meales:<note place="margin">Corn. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos.</note> 
                  <hi>Lex Pompeia</hi> did aſſigne tutors or curators for pupils: by the law <hi>Cornelia,</hi> lands were diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:17391:64"/> By the law <hi>Auguſta, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> did impoſe tributes vpon the people for the publicke good. The Conſul <hi>Falcidius</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted the law <hi>Falcidia,</hi> by which fathers were holden to be carefull for the education of their children. By the law <hi>Sempronia</hi> it was enacted, that no father might diſinhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit his ſonne, not being a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to the Roman Empire.</p>
               <p>But (becauſe the variety of laws is impertinent to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) I will come to the moſt neceſſary conſiderations that princes are to lay before them in making, diſanulling, renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, interpreting, &amp; executing of lawes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in the making of lawes
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:17391:64"/> (as the neceſſitie of time ſhall require) kings are to conſider,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> lib. 2. fol. 27. Ex tractat. de 12. abuſ. Omnium legum eſt inanis cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura niſi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinae Legis imaginem ferat. Aug. de Cin. D. 6. Poſſid. lib. 3 Plat. 4. de rep. 6. de leg.</note> that <hi>lex Dei,</hi> is, <hi>via regalis; quae nec ad dextram, nec ad ſiniſtram declinat.</hi> Firſt, theſe things which doe belong vnto the true worſhip of God, are to be confirmed: next, thoſe things that are conuenient for the commonwealth: then thoſe that are honeſt and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, &amp; thereafter things profitable: the laws made muſt be rather wholeſome then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that they taſte not of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, oppreſſion, or priuat gaine.</p>
               <p>Lawes may bee diſannulled wholly,<note place="margin">Ariſt. 1. in Rhet.</note> when they are repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to religion and pollicy: in part, when ſome things ate to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:17391:65"/> bee changed which formerly the neceſſitie of time, or ſome other cauſes haue tollerated.</p>
               <p>In the interpretation of laws,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de dic. Sapient</note> ſanctity &amp; equitie, rather then the literall meaning are to be reſpected, leſt by wreſted gloſſes, legitimate lawes be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardized, white be made black and blacke white.</p>
               <p>In the execution of laws, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding what good is to be done, what euill is to be repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is required, who are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of reward,<note place="margin">Ariſt. 7. pol Plato. 2.10 de Rep.</note> who of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for the lawes are no leſſe ordayned to defend and prefer the vertuous, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to puniſh the wicked. The execution of laws muſt neither be ouerſtrictly, or remiſſely vrged, but enforced
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17391:65"/> or moderated as occaſion ſhall ſerue, and offenders merit,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> lib. 2. fol. 30. &amp; 85. Seueritas niſi in tra co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gurentes nocentium paeuas ſe coercet, ſaeua cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de liuas eſt. Lact lib. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ius, eſt ſumma iniuria;</hi> when ſeueritie hath his rigour oft times it pulleth vp many goodly plants; which (being manured with clemency) might produce many excellent fruits of obedience, ſeruice and merit.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Amor &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, &amp; proptium co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modum fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iunt ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe Iudicem non agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Ariſt. Rhet. 1.</note> the equall obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of lawes and diſtribution of iuſtice by Princes is careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be looked vnto leaſt the mighty and powerfull offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders eſcape, &amp; onely the weake and poore bee puniſhed and wronged. Old <hi>Cato,</hi> Stoicall <hi>Diogines,</hi> wiſe <hi>Anacharſis,</hi> and many others, did complayne vpon this error, becauſe they
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:17391:66"/> did well know that <hi>it is the height of vniuſtice to execute lawes in equally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Contingit ſepenumero, vt qui parua tollunt depraehenſi pendant, magnorum autem raptores aut ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didi depeculatores (factis argento vijs) euadant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſt. apud Diog. lib. 5. Sine iuſtitia ne Iupiter quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipem agere poteſt. Lud. Viues ſuper Aug. Eurip. in Oreſ.</note>The Princely diſtribution of iuſtice, is nothing elſe but <hi>ſuum cuique tribuere,</hi> is the helme of gouernment, the happineſſe of kings and people. From Iuſtice ariſeth religion, peace, truth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and true friendſhip: in it Princes are to bee noble, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, graue, ſeuere, inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, powerfull, and full of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; neither enclining to the right or left hand, to the rich or poore, but determining all
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:17391:66"/> matters vnder their cenſure,<note place="margin">Anſel. ſuper ep. ad Rom. Ambroſ. de offic.</note> as they looke to bee iudged by that ſupreame Iudge whoſe Lieutenants they are.</p>
               <p>Finally, let ſubordinate Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſo adminiſter iuſtice, as they wil be countable to both their heauenly and earthly maſters; aſſuring themſelues (howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they eſcape here) that there is, <hi>Vnus Iudex, vnum Tribunal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptum, ante illud ſtabunt morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ea in ſella quiſque ſedet qui iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, vbi ſi iniuſte iudicabitur, nec pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunia, nec gratia, nec falſi teſtes, nec deſerti proderunt patroni.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:17391:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XIIII.</hi> Of the wrath of Princes, when and how they ſhould puniſh.</head>
               <p>AS clemency, ſlowneſſe to ire, &amp; proaneſſe to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,<note place="margin">Greg. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. 5.</note> are the diuine and kingly robes of good Princes: ſo furious anger, and deſire of reuenge, are the tyger-like and deformed garments of tyrants by which wiſedome is baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, iuſtice is forgotten, peace is ouerthrowne, the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth ruinated, and the gates of crueltie vnlockt and layd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen:<note place="margin">Eraſ. de Iuſt prin.</note> for this cauſe Princes are carefully (ſetting before them
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:17391:67"/> their fatherly affection to their ſubiects) to reſtraine the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and dangerous inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſuch paſſions, as are preiudiciall to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their people, and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the title and dignity of kings. <hi>Zelus &amp; iracundia minuunt dies, ideo vitanda non tantum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derationis ſed etiam ſenectutis cauſa Cotis</hi> king of <hi>Thracia</hi> (being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally chollerick,<note place="margin">Plut. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po.</note> and a ſeuere puniſher of offences) hauing receiued diuers rare &amp; curious wrought (but fragile) veſſels: (after hee had bountifully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded the giuer) did breake them all, and being asked the cauſe, anſwered; leſt I ſhould be moued to anger, and ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſh my ſeruants for brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:17391:68"/> of them, I haue broken them my ſelfe. This worthy Prince did well know, <hi>that the feare of the king is like the roaring of a Lyon:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouerb. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>and hee that prouoketh him vnto anger, ſinneth againſt his owne ſoule:</hi> and therefore did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue ſuch combuſtible mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as might ſet a fire his death threatning furie. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more oppoſit to counſel and deliberation,<note place="margin">Ira atque cupido con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi. Saluſt. in bell. Iug. Quoties ira animum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uadit, mente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> edoma, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce te ipſum, differ te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus furoris: dum tranquilla mens fuerit, fac quod placet. Greg. Mor.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> temerari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſodaine anger: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bias Priaeneus</hi> preſcribeth delay as a ſoueraigne remedy againſt it: for by intermiſſion, furious paſſions languiſhes, and the myſtie cloudes that oppreſſe the minde either doe vaniſh or become leſſe. <hi>Anthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodorus</hi> the Phyloſopher did
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:17391:68"/> aduiſe <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> at ſuch time as hee was angry, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe twenty foure Greeke letters.</p>
               <p>In puniſhing Princes are to keepe ſuch golden meane and temperate mixture betwixt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and ſeuerity, that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects bee neither wounded by the one, or become inſolent by the other. <hi>Leones quos manſueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere volunt homines, iubebat olim Phraotes verbe ibus non cedi, nes rurſus blanditijs nimium leniendos putabat, quia ſic nimium ſuperbi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euaderent opinibatur, itaque blandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs minis permix is facilius ad mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res optatos poſſe deducere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, in puniſhment (if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity enforce Princes to draw the ſword of Iuſtice) great care
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:17391:69"/> is to be had, that it be done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, as with weeping eyes. Iuſtice without Mercy is as cruell as Mercy without Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is fooliſh:<note place="margin">Bern:</note> for although Iuſtice doth tell Princes, that not to puniſh an euill, is to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of an euill; yet Mercy oft times pardons thoſe that deſerue it not: wounds ought to bee healed not hurt:<note place="margin">Cic. 1. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic.</note> onely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> incureable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are to be cut off: and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ought to be agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the fault, and without partiality; leſt ſome be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and others eſcape: and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, all priuate reſpects in puniſhment are to bee remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de vid.</note> leſt vnder the ſhadow of Iuſtice, cruelty and tyranny be
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:17391:69"/> ſheltered. <hi>Si omnino miſſo ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fuerit opus, conſiderandum eſt Principi ac ſuſtinendum, ne vltra quam ſit neceſſe incidat, cauendum ne maior paena ſit quam culpa, &amp; ne eiſdem de cauſis alij plectantur, alij ne appellentur quidem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XV.</hi> Of two ſorts of flattery, but chiefly of the laſt, that haunts the courts of Princes,</head>
               <p>THere be two chiefe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to vertue in all men, but are more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially preiudiciall to greatnes: the firſt is, the inward <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. de fol. 93.</note> proceeding from home-bred
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:17391:70"/> weakeneſſe, which dayly ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts ſtore of falſe coloured impoſture.<note place="margin">Adulator bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod eſt abſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, &amp; malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod non eſt menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Greg. Mor. 65.</note> The ſecond (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am ſhortly to ſpeake) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the oyly trowell of the ſmooth tong of a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous man, called a flatterer. This laſt ſort of flattery, is a falſe prayſe of that which is not praiſe worthy,<note place="margin">Plato apud Plut. de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mic. &amp; adul.</note> or a ſmooth detracting from the merit of goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Bias apud Plut. ibidem Demoſt. in Philip. decl. 3.</note> the waſpiſh honey of an impudent tongue, the bondage of the eares, the fayned friendſhip of a falſe heart, and the chiefe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil whereon the diuell forgeth his moſt poyſoned weapons: or it is the <hi>Ioab</hi> or <hi>Iudas</hi> like kiſſe of a ſmiling counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the poyſon of truth,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:17391:70"/> playne dealing and honeſty, that (Camelion-like) can turne it ſelfe into all colours,<note place="margin">Plut. de diſt amic. &amp; adul</note> following the fortune of Princes and not themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> (not without cauſe) giueth warning to Princes, of the twofold cunning of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers: Firſt, (ſayth he) they faine ignorance of all matters of moment, whereof loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie ſhould oblige them, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther freely to admoniſh or louingly aduiſe: but in fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous indifferent or light affayres, they ſhew their care and officiouſneſſe. If a Cobweb bee in the Princes Chamber, or a Fuſtian dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet (oft times lined with more true loyalty and ſufficiencie,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:17391:71"/> then ſuch gliſtering worme-ſpun ſtatutes can containe) be in the chamber of preſence the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> keeps the flatterer a ſtur, cryes out vpon his fellow ſeruants, chamber keepers and vſhers: for as knauiſh Empirickes for curing a ſore in the foote,<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Caſſal.</note> cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the haire in the head, or pareth the nayles of the hand: ſo flattering Mountebanks ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer touch thoſe things which they ought,<note place="margin">Beata mens quae nec a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulatur, nec credit adu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milanti. Hier. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>riten. In obſequio comitas ad ſit, adula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io omnium vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum nu trix procul amoueatur. Cic. in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</note> and are onely buſie in matters pernitious or triui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. It is muſicke able to make an honeſt mans teeth ake, to ſee a young Catecumeniſt flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, after ſome ſhort trauels (bought perhaps at a deare rate) at his returne, vent his Matchiuilian foppery with a
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:17391:71"/> ſalutation of <hi>Monſieur ie baſe le vmbre de voſtre gartier:</hi> and at his farewell confirme it with <hi>per Dieu ie ſuis voſtre ſeruitour Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Emolliri a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum fortitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis non eſt, ſed etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ignauiae. Xen. in Cir.</note> this he performeth, not onely to ſuch great ones, in whoſe fauour he would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſinuate himſelfe, but to his very corriuals, whoſe <hi>requiem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam</hi> hee would gladly ſing (for enuy hath euer murdring eyes) but that ſuch <hi>Sinon</hi> ſongs is the true <hi>Canaan</hi> language I much doubt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, (man being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with two faculties,<note place="margin">Plut. de diſt. Amic. &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dul. Iſ. in Sym. Plato in Phedr.</note> ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and irrationall) the one heauenly, delighting in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the other brutiſh, giuen to falſe pleaſures and to the corruption of nature) the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:17391:72"/> either (Athieſt like) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnes the heauenly parts of the ſoule, or takes no notice of them at all; the terreſtriall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts, hee cunningly and couertly foments, vntill ſuch time as the vſe of reaſon is quite extinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>As holeſome meate (ſayth <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) neither nouriſheth the body,<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Caſ.</note> nor ſtrengtheneth the ſinewes,<note place="margin">Princeps adulato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m numero ducat, &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> amicos, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quicquid dixerit, aut fecerit. lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, ſed qui errantem audent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepare. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſo ad Nico.</note> but leaueth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in the ſtomacke: ſo flatterers adde nothing to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vertue, but ſtirre vp vice. If Princes be angry, their flatterers bids them bee reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if they be iealous, they bid them beleeue it: if they be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous, they aduiſe them ſpoile their people: if ſometime Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:17391:72"/> be graciouſly pleaſed to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to their preſence a playne Countrey man (whoſe educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, modeſtie, or baſhfulneſſe hath not taught him in Kings preſence to maske himſelfe with a Brazen Face) then the flatterer laughes, ſcoffes, ieſts, and takes exceptions at euery wrong hayre in his Beard.</p>
               <p>It is cleare then,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. fol. 63.</note> that flatterie is the peſt of Princes, and the ſoft Bed whereon Princes lye, in the Lethargie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſecuritie of Vice; the <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean</hi> Muſike, that drawes them from the true Rule of Reaſon, and diſcerning of Truth: and the gilded pylls, vnder which is hidden moſt deadly poyſon.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:17391:73"/>
               <p>When <hi>Alexander</hi> in drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe had killed <hi>Clitus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Quin. Curt. Gell. lib. 17. Plut. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex.</p>
                     <p>Victus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander pellacibus adula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orum Lenociniis, ita Matri ſcripſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t: Rex Alexander, Iouis Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis filius Olympiadi Matri <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dicit. Atr. in geſt. Alexand. Oroſ. lib. 2. Frequentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitaus initium ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitas. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. 4. hiſt.</p>
                  </note> his flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer <hi>Anaxarchus</hi> was ready to tell him, that he had iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued his death. So long as <hi>Alexander</hi> followed the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aduice of Philoſophy, ſo long did Wiſdome moderate all his actions; then did hee throwe <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> flattering Verſes in the Riuer <hi>Hidaſpes:</hi> but when Flatterie had once whiſpered in his Eare, then Pride, Cruelty, Ambition, and Forgetfulneſſe of Humane Frayltie did intrude in the places of his former Vertues: Then did he kill his true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Seruant, bewayle the want of Worlds, to ſatiate his aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Minde, call himſelfe the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17391:73"/> Sonne of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and forget that he was the Sonne of <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon. <hi>Xerxes</hi> (whoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Graecia was too little to contayne) truſting in flattery, had an ignominious ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw at Thermopylas: One told him, that the Sea groaned vnder the heauy burthen of his Nauy; others, that it was to be feared, that by eſcape of the Enemy he ſhould loſe the triumph of a glorious Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Amongſt many thouſands one faythfull <hi>Demaratus</hi> was onely found; this braue Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier did tell him, that his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Multitude had more weight then ſtrength, was ill to be gouerned, and not to be truſted.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:17391:74"/>
               <p>Sith then there is no ſuch dangerous domeſtike enemyes to Princes, as Flatterers; it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth them (after notice of ſuch attendants, who by flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie inſinuates themſelues in truſt) neerely to diſtinguiſh ſuch <hi>Sicophants</hi> from honeſt men; to diſcountenance them, and not to preferre them to places of credit: ſo long as they are fed,<note place="margin">Agap. ad Iuſt. Plutar. de Amic. et adu. Petrar. lib. 1. Dial. 19. Eraſ. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>po.</note> ſo long ſhall they mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Liberalitie and other Princely Vertues of their <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,</hi> but if he leaue off, or be expoſed to the leaſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe fortune, then ſhall cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Proteus</hi> change his ſhape; when <hi>true attendants are moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious in aduerſitie, and more willingly follow thoſe whom Fortune
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:17391:74"/> hath left. Tarquinius the prowd</hi> (being in exile) did oft times ſay, that he did neuer know his true friend from his flatterer,<note place="margin">Ael. Lamp.</note> till he was neyther able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the one or the other. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Seuerus</hi> did ſo deteſt flattery, that he cauſed <hi>Thuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> a corrupt Flatterer, to bee ſmothered with ſmoake; <hi>Let him</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>that did ſell ſmoake, dye by ſmoake. Ageſelaus</hi> did ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe as his moſt faithfull followers, that did moſt freely admoniſh him; true wiſdome made his vertuous minde to bend rather to that which was good in it ſelfe, then to that which by euill mindes might bee iudged good. <hi>Accepta eos qui bonorum conciliarum te admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:17391:75"/> eſſe volunt, non eos qui adulantur.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XVI.</hi> To whom Princes may ſafely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit publike Functions.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Xen. in Cir. Plato. Pol. Iſo. de Reg.</note>THere is no man ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that will commit the charge of a Shippe, or of his Goods (although of ſmall value) to an ignorant Steereſ-man, or vntruſty Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; neyther wiſe Prince, that will commit the Gouernment of the Common-wealth, the Goods of his Cities, and Liues of his People to ſuch, whom <hi>Homer</hi> calls Deuourers of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.<note place="margin">Homer. Ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. 17.</note>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:17391:75"/> The wrong election or ſuffering of wicked Officers,<note place="margin">Negotijs, quae per te non gerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, viros e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſmodi praefice, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium quae illi commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerint, culpa tibi impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanda ſit. Agap. ad Iuſt. Non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ad nundinas, &amp; Macello e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ijs, qui ſibi gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacula reip. comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> volunt. Plat. in Pol.</note> makes Princes lyable to their faults (the Cenſure being all one, whether Errors be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by themſelues, or their Vice-gerents:) for Princes muſt not onely anſwere to God (whoſe immediate Vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents they are) for themſelues, but for ſuch whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to any part of their charge. Wherefore (ſeeing the good or bad eſtate of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth depends chiefely vpon this choyſe) two conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations are worthy the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of Princes, in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Delegates &amp; Officers: Firſt, that none make merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, or by Money incroach
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:17391:76"/> vpon publike Functions, or wickedly hunt after them: that they bee conferred vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuch, whoſe Life is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt, and their Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſufficient to diſcharge their places: for certainely, the loue of Iuſtice and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, is the leaſt part of the ayme of ſuch who by Money comes vnto preferment; their chiefe deſignes are builded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their priuate gayne, and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of others:<note place="margin">Eraſ. inſtit. prin.</note> by rayſing ſuch to Dignities and Offices, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wrong themſelues, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; themſelues, in promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch as are not worthy; and others, in barring thoſe whoſe merit deſerues prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:17391:76"/>
               <p>Next, becauſe Couetouſneſſe is the moſt dangerous euill in a State,<note place="margin">Caput ſit in omni pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatione negotij, &amp; muneris publici, vt auaritiae pellatur eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am minima ſuſpitio. Cic. 2. offic. Ex Dione Caſſio. Eraſ. 6. apo.</note> and drawes men head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into wickedneſſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie: therefore it concerneth Princes to be carefull, that Iudges and other publike Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers be not onely free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from diſloyalty, bribery, or corruption, but their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers and attendants alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leaſt ſuſpition thereof. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo Pithius</hi> (by Oracle) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the ouerthrow of Sparta: <hi>O Sparta</hi> (ſayd hee) <hi>whoſoeuer is your King, Lady</hi> Pecunia <hi>is Queene, therefore your deſtruction is at hand.</hi> This was a true Oracle from a falſe God, yet worthy the obſeruation in the Morall. <hi>Theopompus</hi> being
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:17391:77"/> asked how Princes might iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gouerne their people?<note place="margin">Ex Plut.</note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, By giuing his Friends no more liberty then is iuſt, and by carefull watching, that ſubordinate Officers vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharge their plaees. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar</hi> oft times did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre his Friends to eminent places of Authority; but they were ſuch, whoſe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency did anſwere his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iuſtice and good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rhein. Lor. Suet. in Caeſ.</note>Secondly, it is neceſſary for Princes, by admonitions and louing exhortations to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Iuſtice and Vprightneſſe to their ſubordinate Delegates; other times, by threatening
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:17391:77"/> and exemplarie puniſhment checke the leaſt ſuſpition of corruption. <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> vſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to exhort his Deputies,<note place="margin">Plut. in Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that they ſhould rather ſtudy Iuſtice and publike good, then the inſatiable deſire of Riches. <hi>Flauius Domitian</hi> did not onely ſeuerely checke ſuſpected Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">Hinc Lex repetunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgata, &amp; ſtrictiſſimè conſeruata fuit: Qua repeteba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur omnes res, vel dolo, vel vi ablatae. Sabell.</note> but did giue way to all ſuch as were wronged by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to enter ſuit againſt them, and did ſeuerely puniſh ſuch as were found guilty. <hi>Epaminon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> hearing a poore man (who had beene long kept in ſuit of Law) complayne of want, did ſend him vnto the Iudge of that Court, where hee was in ſuit, with a Warrant, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a Talent of Money;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:17391:78"/> the Iudge did deliuer it vnto the Beggar, but did humbly petition vnto the King, that hee would be pleaſed to ſhew him the reaſon why hee had impoſed ſuch a great ſumme vpon him? Becauſe (ſayd <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paminondas</hi>) the man whom I ſent, is poore, and honeſt; but thou art rich, and a rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of him and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. A notable example for Princes, to looke vnto ſuch as in Magiſtracie haue indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly encreaſed Riches. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> ſentence againſt ſuch, was, <hi>Qui iniuria afficit pauperem, vt deteſcat ipſe, dabit ditioribus &amp; egebit ipſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acl. Spart.</note> For certainely, no puniſhment will ſo curbe ſuch as are corrupted, as ſometimes
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:17391:78"/> (for example, after lawfull Tryall) to ſeize vpon their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Purchaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrianus Imperator, quos pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peres &amp; innocentes vidit ſponte di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauit; quos calliditate ditatos ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo odio habuit &amp; ad pauperta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem redegit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XVII.</hi> Of Secrecie, in the managing of the weightie affaires of Princes, and what Iuditious Policie Princes may ſometimes lawfully vſe.</head>
               <p>SEcrecie is the beſt and moſt ſure Guardian of great Affaires (to which there is nothing more preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall<note place="margin">Veget. de Re. Mil.</note>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:17391:79"/> then immature diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) and is recommended to Princes as a chiefe Pillar of Empire.<note place="margin">Diog. apud Stob. Omnium difficilimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> areanum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticere, ex dog. Philoſ. Vt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis eſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creta non facile alicuj concredere: ita nemo prudens ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duetit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequi prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana: Eraſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Apo.</note> Counſell without ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie, is like an abortiue birth, brought forth without life; and therefore to be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Wombe of ſecret thoughts. <hi>Salomon</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſayth, <hi>In abſconditis concili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abitur.</hi> Becauſe Secrecie is a moſt difficill Humane action, the ancient Heathen did pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their Gods with one hand vpon their mouth; moralli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, that important Affaires by Princes are onely to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to ſuch, of whoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie and loyaltie they are well aſſured. Great <hi>Alexander</hi> hauing receiued a Letter from
<pb n="339" facs="tcp:17391:79"/> his Mother <hi>Olimpias;</hi> giuing it to his Secretary to reade, did touch his mouth with his Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net; thereby enioyning ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to him. <hi>Philippides</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorite of <hi>Liſymachus,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by his Soueraigne, what Benefit hee deſired to haue conferred vpon him? an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; I refuſe nothing, O King: onely impart no ſecret to me; for it is difficill to keepe counſell, and dangerous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale the ſecrets of a King.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Arcanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tu ſcrutabris vllius vnqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Horat. lib. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Commiſſum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tegas, et vino tortus, et ira.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> cauſed the bones of <hi>Thallus</hi> (who had opened a Letter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to his truſt) to<note place="margin">Suet. in Caeſ.</note>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:17391:80"/> be broken, to the terror of ſuch vntruſtie attendants. This ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie (the neceſſitie whereof is knowne to ſuch who are entred in the firſt elements of State) is ſeconded by the wiſe choyſe of ſuch whom Princes priuately imploy in matters of weight:<note place="margin">Plut. in Poll.</note> For ſometimes, to good ends, both good and bad ſubiects are to be concili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate. And although Princes do deteſt trecherous and wicked followers, yet make they vſe of both ſorts, for the effecting of good and commendable purpoſes.<note place="margin">Eſt quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta, atque commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis callidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. Baſ.</note> Which politike parts of Gouernment (otherwiſe then they fall out) cannot be reduced to a definite number, neyther bee better illuſtrated
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:17391:80"/> then by precedent Examples, and are to be vſed according to the neceſſitie of time.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Qui regnare volunt multis dormire ſagaci</l>
                  <l>Multaque concilio diſsimulare ſolent.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hannibal</hi> hauing reſolued to beleaguer Sagunth,<note place="margin">Liu. lib. 2. Bell. Prin. 2.</note> did bring his Army againſt another Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, leſt his intention againſt Sagunth ſhould be diſcouered. Another time the ſame <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> did ſpare a field of Corne that did belong to his enemy <hi>Fabius;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Val. lib. 7. cap. 3.</note> thereby giuing cauſe of ſuſpition to the Senate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Fabius. This cunning clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed practice might haue ſomewhat preuayled, if the Pietie of</hi> Fabius <hi>and Pollicie of</hi> Hannibal <hi>had
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:17391:81"/> not beene well knowne to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes Wiſdome adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Princes rather to winke at capitall Offences,<note place="margin">Trebell. Pol. Diſſimulat iniuriam callidus, at ſtultus ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim prodit iram ſuam. Pro. 12.13. Liu. lib. 3. Bell. Prin. 2. Omnia Hannibali hoſtium non ſecus quam ſua nota erant. Liu. 22.</note> then violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in an vnfit time, to bewray their iuſtly conceiued diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>Marcus Marcellus</hi> hearing that ſome of his Councell had priuate intelligence with his Enemy <hi>Hannibal,</hi> did conceale his knowledge, till ſuch time as <hi>Hannibal</hi> was paſt hope of taking the City Nola: Then did he ſhut his Gates, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then his Guards, and call the Conſpirators to an accompt.</p>
               <p>Amongſt all theſe, and many other Pollicies, there is none more profitable for State, then to haue good intelligence of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:17391:81"/> the Affayres of Enemyes, or of ſuch, of whoſe friendſhip Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are leaſt ſecured; to prie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Strength, Intentions, &amp; Preparations. The Carthagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians fearing the Power of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fron. lib. 1. cap. 2. Plut in Poſ. lib. 2.</note> did ſend a Citizen of courage (as baniſhed) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the protection of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> who being retayned, did skrew himſelfe into the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and diſcouer his Intention to the State of Carthage. Theſe, and the like, be the wiſe Pollicies of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: all which are euer to be warranted by a ſafe conſcience and good ends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vbi Leonina pellis non pertingit, oportet Vulpinam (ſed ſemper ad bonum finem) aſſuere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:17391:82"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XVIII.</hi> Vpon whom Eccleſiaſticall Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by Princes are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred.</head>
               <p>THere be three inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſole felicity of wel-gouerned Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealths doe depend:<note place="margin">Greg. in Regiſt.</note> The firſt, is the right education of Youth; the ſecond, Religious and holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; the third, Vpright and Iuſt Magiſtrates: Without the firſt, the ſecond and third can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubſiſt; and without the ſecond, the firſt and third are without effect: for without
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:17391:82"/> good education there can bee neither holy Paſtor, nor iuſt Magiſtrate: without religion Learning and Iuſtice are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable: for this cauſe,<note place="margin">Epiſcopi ſacris literis eruditi ſint, Patres non Domini Hier. ad. Paul. &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Luc. &amp; Epiſt. Paul.</note> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are carefully to prouide, that the care of the ſoules of their people bee not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to wicked or ignorant Paſtors. <hi>Cauſa ſunt ruinae populi ſacerdotes mali, quoniam peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum participes fiunt qui miniſteria, quod aiunt, portantibus aſinis cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram animarum crediderunt, aut ineptos homines exemplaria poſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> Church benefices are not raſhly to be conferred vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one, but vpon ſuch, who in good workes,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.6. 2. Paral. 17. 1. Tim. 1. Pet. 2.3.</note> ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and irreproueable life are worthy of ſo high a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:17391:83"/> Good king <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> is a patterne for ſucceeding Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in making choyce, and preferring men learned and holy:<note place="margin">Princeps dignos ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in via do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos eliget, ac beneficijs ornabit, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> currentes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uehet lupos hiantes. Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor: Etym. cap. 2. Nauis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorum tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus lateri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta eſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, cordis puritate conſcientia bona, &amp; fide non ficta. Bernard. in feſt. Magd. Serm.</note> for none can preach ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they bee ſent; and none are ſent who by ſimony, pride and ambition, or other indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect meanes intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the Lords harueſt, ſeeking their priuate ends, and not Gods glory.</p>
               <p>Finally, as <hi>Plato</hi> did thinke no man fit for gouernment, but ſuch who did vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vndergoe the heauy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thereof: So Princes are to preferre none to Eceleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call functions but godly, learned, &amp; honeſt men, whoſe merit rather then deſire of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:17391:83"/> challengeth ſuch place. <hi>Princeps imprimis eos ſuſpectos habeat, qui ſe negotijs ingerunt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitioſi, qui ſua quaerunt, non quae Dei ſunt, qui denique voti compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, vel praece vel praecio fieri con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tendunt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XIX.</hi> Of Church controuerſies, ciuill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, ſeditious Pamphlets, infamous Libels, and how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully by Princes they are to bee repreſſed.</head>
               <p>ALL Controuerſies may bee reduced to Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall or Ciuill: ſuch as concerne the Church are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:17391:84"/> touching the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, or high myſteries of ſaluation, of which it is true. <hi>Non ſeruatur vnitas in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo niſi eadem ſit in colendo:</hi> Or they are of matters of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, Church policie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different; the firſt are broached and entertained, either by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſts, Idolatrous, ſuſpitious Hereticks, or conceited Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes; the ſecond are ſet on foote and vpholden by ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">Sunt quos ambitio im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: qui priuatim degeneres, in publicum exitioſi, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſpei niſi per diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias habent Tac. 11. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> ambitious, ſingular or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant perſons, who preferre fiſhing in turbulent waters &amp; their own priuate ends to their duty to Princes, their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their ſuperiours, to the care of their flocke, or peace of the Church, accounting it their
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:17391:84"/> chiefeſt honour to call in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion things indifferent, and by refractory, repugnancy, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te contra dicendi omnia in dubium vertere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plato de ſcient.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I wil not enter into the firſt ſort of Church controuerſies, becauſe they are ſufficiently conuinced by the ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and many orthodoxall Councels. The controuerſies themſelues of the ſecond ſort are alſo already determined by the generall conſent of the Church, and writings of many religious and no leſſe learned: neither doe I intend to plow the ſpacious fields of ciuill contentions, I leaue them to the wiſedome of Princes,<note place="margin">Tit. cap. 3.10.</note> and to ſuch graue and learned
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:17391:85"/> Iudges to whom the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate determining of cauſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſubiects is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: I wil onely (in few words) touch the ſeuerall parts of my deuiſion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Athieſts, Idolatrous, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious heretickes, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate ſchiſmatickes, are ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſound doctrine and charitable perſwaſions to bee reduced to the right way,<note place="margin">Tit. cap. 3.10.</note> or (as tares from the wheate, or the ſowre leauen of the Phariſes) to be diſtinguiſhed and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from loyall and dutifull ſubiects, leſt the good be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, or the whole lumpe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. The others, who affects certain cognizances &amp; badges of curioſity, <hi>Anarchie,</hi> confuſed
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:17391:85"/> parity, or falſe named purity, (euer holden dangerous in all ſound gouernment) &amp; ſeeks to correſpond amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; be ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church (not knowing, or not ſeeming to know, <hi>tam ſunt mores quidam ſchiſmatici quam dogmata ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica</hi>) I leaue them to the care of ſuch prouident Princes as (without doubt) in a fit time will obuiate ſuch euils as with draws the obedience of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, or diſturbes the peace of the Church. If my requeſt might haue due reſpect amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt ſuch perſons,<note place="margin">Satagunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirentes &amp; quae ſubter ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am ſunt &amp; ſupra coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. Tacit. 4 Anal. Ioan. 19.23.</note> I ſhould ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſh that they would wiſely perpend, that the ſupreme Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop did recommend peace vnto the Church, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſowes diſſention in the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:17391:86"/> Church, rents the ſeameleſſe coate of the Lord of the church: that without brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue,<note place="margin">Qui ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Deum eſt zela à ſuperna po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendet, &amp; diuina qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derata con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnaque ratione gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernatur. Niceph. Greg. lib. 6. Chryſ. ſup. Iohan. hom 7.</note> blinde zeale doth not profit, but leades to deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Vbi zelus &amp; contentio ibi incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia &amp; omne opus prauum.</hi> That the bonds of religion are our faith, our baptiſme, and not our ceremony, our policy: that ſuch who are giuen to vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnneceſſary contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, vnſwadles the church of her bonds of peace, opens a gap to all diſorder and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.12 25.11.16.</note> giues aduantage to the common enemy to make mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke by their diſcord. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remember that <hi>inſanae diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones a Satana ſuggeruuntur.</hi> That they would doe much
<pb n="353" facs="tcp:17391:86"/> better to leaue the turbulent and ouer-weaning Opinions of theſe Times, and reuiue the bleſſed proceedings of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Fathers of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, which was in the like or greater caſes, not to enter into aſſertions and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous poſitions, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer counſels and aduices. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was content to ſay, <hi>Ego &amp; non Dominus ſecundum concilium meum.</hi> Laſtly,<note place="margin">Sine impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio nec do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus vlla, nec ciuitas, nec gens, nec homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſtare, nec rerum natura om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, nec ipſe mundus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Cic. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1 de legibus.</note> my ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire ſhould be, that all ſuch as haue loſt the charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of loue, and by fire-brands of inconſidered zeale haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed the patience of Princes, by ſtirring vp needleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, and haue neglected ſuperiour powers, by contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:17391:87"/> the authority of their mother the Church might wiſely conſider, that <hi>hominis eſt errare, ſed nullius niſi inſipientis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerare in errore.</hi> That where offences are incorrigible, the ſlownes of Iuſtice is retaliated by the ſeuerity of puniſhment. That ſcepters haue eyes, and Princes long hands that will ſee and ouer-reach their moſt ſecret and far diſtant actions of this quality.</p>
               <p>The ciuil diſſentions that do concern Princes to looke vnto are either betwixt ſubiect and ſubiect vpon ſome inueterate malice, or new conceiued qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, and are to be appeaſed by louing admonitions or royall authority: or they are <hi>propter
<pb n="355" facs="tcp:17391:87"/> meum &amp; tuum,</hi> for titles to goods or lands, &amp; are to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned according to equity and law, the right vſe whereof is <hi>ſuum cuique tribuere,</hi> &amp; rather to determine matters of weight then to authoriſe,<note place="margin">Plut. in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</note> multiplicity of wranglings, vnbrotherly contentions, &amp; endles ſuites a-amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt ſubiects: wherby their eſtates are either weakened or ruinated. <hi>Iam quidem omnino delictum eſt in vobis quod liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioſa iudicia habetis inter vos.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9 7.</note> This vncharitable going to Lawe, and endleſſe ende of Law hath euer beene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemd the fruits of Athiſme, contentious ſpirits or idleneſſe and eminent badges (howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cloked) of corruption
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:17391:88"/> and iniuſtice: For this cauſe, the checking and abridging of the impertinencie and delay of Suits belongs vnto ſupreme Magiſtrates and ſubordinate Iudges.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. fol. 92.</note> 
                  <hi>Lis de rebus facile cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptibilibus celeriter debet termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari vel res vendi, ne legibus fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data ciuitas, legibus euertatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the infected Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Church-controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, ciuill contentions and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious courſes by them ariſing doe flow the poyſonable Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Enuy,<note place="margin">Cic. in Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>til 2. Tacit. 1. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Saluſt. orat. fil. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merè vitam regentium iudicare. Greg. Mor.</note> Malice, Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, Vncharitable cenſure, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious and infamous Libels, not onely againſt the perſons of priuate men, but againſt Princes and ſuperior Powers, againſt whom wee are not to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:17391:88"/> thinke an ill thought, al which machinations, and (<hi>Catiline</hi>-like) firebrands, are to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as the monſtrous births of Parricides and Traytors, or the intemperate extrauagant councels of light perſons, (that thriue beſt in the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſtate) and are lyable to the ſeuerity of exemplary puniſhment to bee inflicted vpon the Authors, deuulgers keepers or allowers of ſuch helliſh traſh as infatuates the hearts of the fooliſh light vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,<note place="margin">Multitudo omnis ſicut mare mobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſt qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus, in pace turbae ſunt. Liu 28</note> with a ſiniſter miſpriſion of beſt actions, and brands the authors with all ſuch taints as diſgrace may acumulate vpon ſuch diſloyall ſubiects. The contagion of this diſeaſe (as
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:17391:89"/> the waters that gain a breach) is to bee ſtopped at the firſt, leaſt ſuch inundations ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow the fields of dutifull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and bring contempt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on authority. <hi>Omne malum naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens facile opprimitur: inueteratum fit plerumque robuſtius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XX.</hi> Of the liberalitie of Princes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHilip</hi> of Macedon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aduiſed to puniſh <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canor</hi> (who had vniuſtly detracted from the merite of ſo worthy a Prince) anſwered,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:17391:89"/> 
                  <hi>Nicanor non eſt Macedonum peſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex Plut.</note> 
                  <hi>videndum eſt igitur ne nos ceſſamus in officio:</hi> This wiſe Prince knowing <hi>Nicanor</hi> to bee poore, did preſently giue order that a guift ſhould bee ſent vnto him;<note place="margin">Tutius Principi munificen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficentia ſibi conſiliare beneuolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; amari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui. Eraſ. apo.</note> ſome few daies after (by the ſame informer) it was told to <hi>Phillip</hi> that <hi>Nicanor</hi> did much magnifie him: You ſee then, ſayde hee, that it is in the power of Princes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to cure the diſeaſes of ſcandalous tongues.</p>
               <p>As God is liberality it ſelfe, is bountifull to all men needeth not, nor requireth any gaine, onely affecteth the ſacrifice of a true penitent and right thankefull heart:
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:17391:90"/> ſo true liberality not onely conciliates the loue of ſubiects but maketh (in ſome ſort) the faces of Princes, to ſhine with the goodneſſe of their Maker, in the diſtribution of their goods without reſpect of reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation or gaine. They doe vſe their people as good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards their ſheepe, they feede them vpon the greene and wholeſome paſtures of muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence and liberalitie,<note place="margin">Xen. in Cir.</note> and do not ſuffer them to range in the barren deſerts of pouerty, to bee torne with thorny bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, neither to be a prey to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring Wolues.<note place="margin">Inſtabiles d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uitiae flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orum imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taritur cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum. Agap. ad Iuſt.</note> Wolues. They doe well know that earthly riches are vncertaine, not permanent, but periſhing, temporary and
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:17391:90"/> dayly transferred from one to another, gotten with care,<note place="margin">Beneficen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ſtabilis eſt poſſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus cum Beroal. de Op.</note> kept with danger, and left with ſorrow; but munificence and liberality are firme per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent and perpetual, purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by vertue, exerciſed with ioy, and recorded vpon the table of in obliterable true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. This due conſideration will make liberall <hi>Titus Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> bewayle the day wherein he had done no good. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Seuerus</hi> inuite the poore &amp; indigent to bee beholden to him.<note place="margin">Cum ſit v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> modus, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que peccat quod exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, quam quod deſcit Sence. de benef.</note> But although long di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe embelliſhed by a reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> with all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of art could adde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the perfection or due prayſe of this Princely vertue:
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:17391:91"/> yet leſt the poore virgine libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie become proſtitute and common, ſhe is to bee confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within her owne limits, and tyed to the following cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. Firſt, (becauſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue conſiſts in the mean) Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are iuditiouſly to examine their ability leſt they giue more then they may,<note place="margin">Diog. apud Stob.</note> or leſſe then they ſhould. They are not to giue too much, leſt in wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the channell they empty the ſpring: nor too little leſt they empayre theyr royall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. They are not to giue to all men, becauſe the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable belly of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude can neuer bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. <hi>Si paſsim, ſi omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:17391:91"/> quis finis?</hi> Their libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie muſt bee chiefly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, <hi>Virtute preditis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digentibus, aut bene merenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus;</hi> to the vpright vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous that ſtands in neede, or to the well deſeruing: if ſometimes they giue to the vitious it is in commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theyr wants or in hope of theyr amendment,<note place="margin">Benificium ab homine duro &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpero datum panis lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſus eſt, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienti exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium, eſt tamen acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Senec. de benef.</note> and not to add matter to theyr in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent life, <hi>Qui homini ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam dat, non homini dat ſed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitati.</hi> Next the time of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing (conſiſting in timely gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and not keeping ſutors in ſuſpence) is worth the obſeruation: <hi>Bis dat qui cito dat:</hi> timely liberality ſheweth a free and true noble willingneſſe,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:17391:92"/> and delayes doe diſcouer a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary conſent, looſeth the guift and the thankfulneſſe of the acceptant. The place of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing is rather to be priuate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> publicke, <hi>Beneficia non ſunt reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa niſi cogat neceſsitas nec ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probanda apud memores:</hi> true libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality can neuer abide phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call oſtentation, neither doe goodneſſe and charity partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate with hypocriſie, hope of gaine, or glorious ſhewes. <hi>Id pie iuſte humaniter fit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Recte facit qui ſilentio tegit opus ſuum, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatibus ſingulorum occulte ſub uenit. Amb. 1. offic.</note> 
                  <hi>quod ſine ſpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendi fit.</hi> Laſtly, the benifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of Princes is to bee of their owne goods, not vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken from one and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon another, leaſt the grudge of the wronged, exceed the loue of receiuers. <hi>Qui alijs
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:17391:92"/> nocent, vt in alios liberales ſint non benefici nec liberales, ſed pernicioſi iudicandi ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XXI.</hi> Of the mutuall friendſhip; and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence that ought to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene neighbouring Princes and contiguous kingdomes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAlomon</hi> preferreth a friend that is neere to a brother,<note place="margin">Prouerb. 27.10.</note> that is farre of,<note place="margin">Chremes ille Terenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinqua a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitiae parte ponit vicinitatem Plut. in apo.</note> intimating thereby that neighberhood &amp; vicinitie of place, hath a chiefe intereſt in the degrees of frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> hauing a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of ground to ſell, gaue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Cryer to make it
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:17391:93"/> more vendible, to adde the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of his neighbors. The dolefull experience of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny famous nations, noble houſes by bloody warres and diſſentious, now ruined and deſolate,<note place="margin">Atrox pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis vicinus malus, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra maxima commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. Heſiod. de Agricul.</note> doe demonſtrate that the intertaynement of neighbouring friendſhip and mutuall reſpect, is a redoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſtrength of kingdomes, and maintayner of families: <hi>Omnis vis vnita plus eſt, quam multiplicata. Aetoli &amp; Acarnani in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſe mutuis cladijs euerterunt.</hi> By diſcord the noble fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of <hi>Scillans</hi> and <hi>Marians, Caeſarians</hi> and <hi>Pompeians</hi> were ouerthrowne. But if I had the penſill of <hi>Apelles</hi> I ſhould neuer bee able to giue the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:17391:93"/> due proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; liuely colours to neighboring friendſhip: but (leauing the Art that farre tranſcends my reach) I one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe commend vicinitie and vnited ſtrength,<note place="margin">Nihil tua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum facile inter ib it, ſi habeas vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui ſtatim in periculo ſuccurat. Heſiod.</note> as the chiefe humane bleſſing imparted to Kings or people: Firſt, by the vtter euerſion or irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerable loſſe of ſuch famous kingdomes and honourable families as now (by bloody warres and iarres) are either deſolate or not ſcarre-cured.<note place="margin">Diſcordia atque ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio omnia oportunio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra facit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidiantibus Liu. decad. lib. 4.</note> And ſecondly, by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicitie of benefites and the moſt wholeſome fruites of peace, plentie, loue, free intercourſe, and common ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie: all which by ſciſſure and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:17391:94"/> and diſrenting of the hearts &amp; affections of ſuch whom the maker of all things hath fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in one mould (euer oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to humane policie,<note place="margin">Diſſentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> debent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mari, ſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquando aut charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem probant aut à chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate naſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Aug. Epiſt. 87.</note> and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to diuine cenſure) are quite ouerthrowne and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed.</p>
               <p>For theſe and many other cauſes (which I might aleadge) good Princes are carefull (if it be poſſible) to be at peace with all Chriſtian Princes, whom they vſe as their brethren and friends, conciliating them by Princely offices,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. fol. 55.</note> mutuall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, euer doing to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as they would others ſhould do vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but more neerely they tender the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of ſuch who liues within
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:17391:94"/> the precinct of their territories &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, them they ſtriue to vnite in religion, lawes, and hearts. <hi>Facile coit amicitia inter eos quos lingua communis regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num propinquitas, ingeniorum ac morum ſimilitudo conſiliat.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XXII.</hi> Of warre: what Princes are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they enter in warre; for what cauſes they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take armes, and how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues in warre.</head>
               <p>ALL warre may be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in royal, ciuill,<note place="margin">Iſid. lib. 2.</note> more then ciuill &amp; perſonall warre. I call that royall warre
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:17391:95"/> which is be betwixt king and king, kingdome &amp; kingdome, which (as ſome doe affirme) was begun,<note place="margin">Lucan. lib. 1 Geneſ. 14.16. Varro. Diod. Sic. Quint. Cur. de geſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex.</note> and had the name of <hi>Bellum</hi> from <hi>Belus</hi> ſonne to <hi>Ninus</hi> and did begin in Aſſiria: others that <hi>Chedelaamor</hi> king of the Elamits; others affirm that <hi>Prometheus</hi> was the firſt that tooke armes. Such royall war was betwixt <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> Rome &amp; Carthage. Ciuill warre is betwixt neighbor and neighbour, citie and citie, ſuch was betwixt the <hi>Hannonians</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſdrubal;</hi> in Rome betwixt the <hi>Pompeians</hi> and <hi>Caeſarians.</hi> More then ciuill warre is betwixt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſon,<note place="margin">Tit. Liu.</note> couſen and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, vnckle and nephew; ſuch was betwixt <hi>Herod Aſcalon</hi> and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:17391:95"/> his two ſonnes, <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> betwixt <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> at the battle of <hi>Pharſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> where did lye dead the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther killed by the ſonne,<note place="margin">Ioan. Car.</note> the brother by the brother, and the couſen by the couſen; and if wee will come neereer ſuch bloody warre was in England, betwixt the houſe of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Yorke</hi> now happily vnited.<note place="margin">Seru. in. Ae. neid. Virg.</note> Perſonal warre is the debating of ſome matter of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence, and ſomtimes for the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of matters of ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, betwixt prince &amp; prince, ſubiect &amp; ſubiect, &amp; of al other ſorts of war (<hi>Dauids</hi> fight with <hi>Goliah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.50.</note> and the like excepted) leaſt warrantable amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,<note place="margin">Quint. Cur.</note> far leſſe amongſt princes
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:17391:96"/> vpon whoſe ſafetie dependeth the publicke good) whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not to be committed to ſingular hazards: ſuch war was betwixt <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> for the mariage of <hi>Sabina Heretrix</hi> to the kingdome of Albanie, betwixt the Emperor <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> and <hi>Maxentius.</hi> But I will leaue the curious deuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of warre,<note place="margin">Omnis pax à deo eſt Greg. lib. 17</note> and ſhortly ſpeake of that warre which is royall. I doe confeſſe that peace is the Nurſe of all happineſſe, and the arch bleſſing that (by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty) is imparted,<note place="margin">Pacis bono omnia bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na conſtant Aug. de ciu. dei. c. 19. Eccleſ. 3.</note> either to Princes or people, yet can I not deny that there is a time of warre, wherein Princes may lawfully take armes: <hi>Duo ſunt decertandi genera vnum iure legum,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:17391:96"/> alterum per vim, confugiendum eſt ad poſterius, ſi non ſatis eſt vti ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riori;</hi> when reaſon is extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed then force may ſucceede:<note place="margin">Bonus prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabitur ad bella geren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, ſed pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentior ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendet qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit inter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem paci ac beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiae natu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animal &amp; inter feras belluas pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dationi ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas. Rhein Ler.</note> yet before attempting warre, Princes are wiſely to expend the difficulties and bloody dangers that doe attend warre. That they truly inform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of the cauſes which moue them, of their abilitie to vphold ſo ſumptuous a charge: they are ſeriouſly to meditate with themſelues, and debate with their Councell vpon the irrecouerable loſſes, the chaos of confuſion, the multitude of miſeries, the inhumane cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, the ſhipwracke of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the ſpoyles, rapes, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies, murthers, cares, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:17391:97"/> loſſes, cryes of fatherleſſe and widdowes, and vpon the Ocean of euils that do accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany al-deuouring warre; they are wiſely to conſider the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe charges, that vpholds it, the encreaſe and multiplying of it, the eaſie beginning, the difficult and vncertayne iſſue of bloody warre, and that they muſt not ſeeke to obtayn that with blood and ſhame,<note place="margin">Quam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitoſa &amp; res ſcelerata bellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hinc malorum omnium quaſi mare quoddam exundat ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſerit ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitatum fluctibus operit bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. Eraſm. inpaneg. ad phil.</note> which they can neither get nor keepe, without ſin. Theſe and the like euils are able to check the inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate deſires of ambitious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging of dominions, of vayn glory, or tyrannous reuenge. Princes are to call to mind that innocent blood is botled in heauens treaſure; that there is
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:17391:97"/> a ſtrict account for the leaſt drop of humane blood, ſpent in their default. To this they may add the fraylty of the life of man, the millions of diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hourely accidents, and fatal blowes that dayly beſides war aſſaults the ruinous Cottage wherein the life of man is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, let them deſcend to the true cauſes of warre, (from which are to bee exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ambition of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the confidence in the number of <hi>Xerxes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bella ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienda vt iniquitatis cauſa tolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pacis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatem. Aug. contra Fauſt.</note> the couetouſnes of <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſus,</hi> and priuate ends of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi>) Gods glory, the defence of kingdomes from forrayne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury and enioying of peace, are the true cauſes that ought to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:17391:98"/> ſound the trumpet in <hi>Sion,</hi> and vnſheath the regall ſword:<note place="margin">Ex Plut.</note> theſe moued <hi>Dauid</hi> to put his hand to the ſling: <hi>Iudas Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus</hi> boldly goe againſt Gods enemies; many braue Princes to contemne death in his face, for the honour of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame King, and ſafety of their Countreys. <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> did ſay that warre ought to bee commanded by the Gods, iuſtified by Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, maintayned by Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and executed by wiſe Captaynes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and couragious Souldiers.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. fol. 55.</note> Princes then for the aboue named cauſes (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue lawfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced warre in publicke and honourable forme) may
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:17391:98"/> lawfully take armes; wherein they muſt bee religious, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, iudicious, iuſt, politike, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant, skilfull, ſtrict obſeruers of diſcipline, and mercifull. So long as <hi>Moſes</hi> lifted vp his hands, ſo long had the people victory. Prouident <hi>Scipio</hi> did ſcorne to ſay <hi>non putarem,</hi> I did not thinke it ſhould fall out thus. Iudicious <hi>Alexander</hi> made rather choyce of few skillfull,<note place="margin">In alijs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſi quid erratum eſt poteſt poſt modum corrigi, prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orum delicta e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem non re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Veget. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> then of confuſed multitudes. Iuſt <hi>Seleucus</hi> did rather ſhare in one Eye with his ſonne, then to bee taynted with iniuſtice. Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke <hi>Sertorius</hi> was more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in counſel then ſtrength. <hi>Peſcennius</hi> did watch when his ſouldiers did ſleepe. Skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:17391:99"/> 
                  <hi>Hannibal</hi> did range his battels to diſaduantage his enemies.<note place="margin">Val. Max.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> did ſo ſtrictly obſerue Military di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, that he did puniſh the leaſt contempt thereof. Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Mithridates</hi> did not inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly triumph ouer his van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed enemies.</p>
               <p>Next, in the hazards of war Princes are to be neither care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſely nor timerouſly ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the euent which may ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterly ſucceed,<note place="margin">Optimus locus inbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo eſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. quia for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes tenent locum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium inter timidos &amp; audaces. Ariſt. polit.</note> but iealous &amp; head-full in dangers, ſtretching and tentering their wit vpon the racke of inuention, till their ſetled and ſteele-armed reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may boldly aduenture the chance of Dice, &amp; attempt their fortune. The Emperour
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:17391:99"/> 
                  <hi>Lucullus</hi> vſed to ſay, <hi>ſe malle v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num militem ſuume manibus hoſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eripere, quam vniuerſas hoſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> copias ſibi vendicare. Hannibal</hi> to this ſame purpoſe ſayth, <hi>Se magis cunctantem &amp; acquieſcentem Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium, quam pugnantem Marcellum formidare.</hi> It hath euer beene the wiſedome of greateſt Captains rather by pollicies, ſtratagems,<note place="margin">Ael. Spart.</note> and wiſedome to ouerthrow the enemy, then by hazards &amp; vncertain battle,<note place="margin">Eutrop. lib. 3. Caeſ. de bell Iſoc. ad Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocl. Reg.</note> and rather by councell then by force. <hi>Lacones ſi quando ſtratagemmate, hoc eſt Callido conſilio hoſtem ſuperaſſent, Marti bouem immolabant, ſin aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to praelio gallum; hoc pacto conſue facientes belli duces, vt non ſolum fortes eſſent ad praelium verum vt callidis potius conſilijs aduerſus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:17391:100"/> inſtructi, victoriam incruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam conſequerentur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In warre alſo magnanimity and courage in moſt eminent dangers is requiſit; becauſe the quality of warre is ſuch, that the fearefulnes of one, diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth others. Wherefore baſe feare (the badge and terror of peaſants) doth not beſeeme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Princes:<note place="margin">Plut. in Pol.</note> for certainly where feare is, there can bee ſmall hope of victorie. <hi>Iudas Machabeus</hi> (enuironed by the multitude of enemies) was aduiſed to turne backe.<note place="margin">1. Mac. c. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> God forbid (ſayd he) that we ſhould do this thing to fly from them if our time become let vs dye manfully for our brethren, and let vs not ſtain our honor. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drias</hi>
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:17391:100"/> captaine of the <hi>Spartans,</hi> being demaunded why his people did make choyce,<note place="margin">Suet. lib. 5.</note> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of death then to yeeld to the enemy; becauſe (ſayd he) it is a law obſerued amongſt them, rather to offer theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to death then to captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <hi>Bias</hi> (hauing warre with <hi>Iphicrates</hi> King of the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi>) being ſurprized by an vnexſpected ambuſh,<note place="margin">Val. Max:</note> and ſeeing his people abandon him did thus encourage or rather checke their cowardiſe:<note place="margin">Trog. Pom.</note> tell you, ſaid he, to the liuing, that I your Captaine do die fighting; and I ſhall tell to the dead, that you did leaue me like cowards. The ſtrength of the Aſſirians was in the courage of their
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:17391:101"/> commander <hi>Belus:</hi> of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> in <hi>Cirus:</hi> of the <hi>Thebans,</hi> in <hi>Hercules:</hi> of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> in <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Macchabeus:</hi> of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> in <hi>Alcibiades:</hi> of the <hi>Troians</hi> in <hi>Hector:</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> in <hi>Ogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:</hi> of the <hi>Epirotes,</hi> in <hi>Pirrhus:</hi> of the <hi>Romans</hi> in <hi>Scipio:</hi> of the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians</hi> in <hi>Hannibal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe &amp; the like it is cleere that moe famous victories, &amp; more proſperous ſucceſſe hath happened, by the wiſedome, dexterity, and courage of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Commanders, then by the ſtrength of ſouldiers arms.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, becauſe warre (as all humane actions) muſt haue an end, the ſeuerall iſſues of warre preſent a three-fold conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Firſt, if Princes attaine to
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:17391:101"/> the moſt fortunate ſucces that can bee wiſhed, they are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly to curbe their immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ioyes, inſulting pride, and inhumane cruelty, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring <hi>Ezechiels</hi> wheeles (coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited by the Poets, <hi>in rota fortun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi>) whereby is denoted the volubility of worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, that the euent which falleth this day to the victor, may fall the next to the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed. <hi>Fortuna vitrea eſt cum ſplendet frangitur.</hi> When <hi>Dauid</hi> did heare of the death of <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. Quin. Cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Saluſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> ſee the head of <hi>Pompey,</hi> Great <hi>Alexander, Darius</hi> dead in his preſence; <hi>Marcus Marcellu, Siracuſe</hi> burned; <hi>Scipio Numance</hi> deſtroyed; and <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal</hi> behold the proſtrate Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:17391:102"/> ſorrowfull wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and fatherleſſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Cannas.</hi> Theſe great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did teſtifie by (their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerate plaints and bitter teares) the ſorrow they did conceiue at the fall of their moſt obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate enemies; for pittifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the miſerable, is the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of mercy, &amp; compaſſionate ſorrowes are able to extract teares from ſtone-hearted cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty: Much more from ſuch good Princes as are ſecondary patternes of clemency and mercy. <hi>Epimanundas cum alias hilari vultu ſolitus eſt in publicum prodire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baſil. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Ambr. ad Vercel. Ep.</note> 
                  <hi>poſtridie eius diei quo feliciter pugnatum eſt in leuctris, proceſsit ſqualidus &amp; ſubmiſſus; amicis cauſam ſciſcitantibus, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:17391:102"/> inquit, ſed heri,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hier. in Gloſ. ſup. Math. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſenſi me plus aequo mihi placuiſſe, eius gaudij in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperantiam hodie caſtigo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, if the victory en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to the enemy, wiſe and couragious Princes are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to contemne matter of ſuch importance,<note place="margin">Eurip. in Phaeniſ. Demoſt. ex arg. lib. Plato apud Stob.</note> neither to bee (cowardlike) deiected; <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractis rebus violentior vltima vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> they are to recollect themſelues with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that vnconſtant warre ſometimes exalts the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſubdues the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: <hi>Grauiſsimae ſunt morſus irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatae neceſsitatis;</hi> therefore they are to vſe the beſt meanes in their iuſt cauſes, to recouer their loſſes, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the way to an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:17391:103"/> peace, or with their reunited forces, try the more fauourable aſpect of death-thundring <hi>Mars.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Demoſt. in or. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uneb. Cic. ad ſeru</note> Time admits not many words where dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger knockes at the doore: <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia experire more anguium, qui ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite obtrito cauda minantur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third and laſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is in binding vp of peace, wherein Princes are to ſhew themſelues confident in arms. <hi>Sub Clipeo melius ſuccedit pacis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotium:</hi> They are ſo to negotiate that their laying downe of armes,<note place="margin">Plato. de Rep. Cic. 2. Phil. 2. Veget. lib. 2. Liu. lib. dec 10.</note> may bee vpon ſure and honourable conditions. <hi>Vt vere pax eaſit, non pactio ſeruirtutis.</hi> But when Princes know their own weakneſſe, and the powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their enemies, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:17391:103"/> aduiſeth them to yeeld to ſuch conditions, as by the dextrous managing of matters of ſuch importance they can procure. <hi>Sit pax aliquando,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emachus apud Plut. in apo.</note> 
                  <hi>quauis tuta conditione, nam gubernator v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi naufragium timet, licet iactura, quicquid ſanari poteſt redimit, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitati parendum, quam ne dij quidem ſuperant:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XXII.</hi> Of Souldiers and Militarie diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</head>
               <p>THe name <hi>Miles,</hi> or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour (after the building of Rome) was by <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:17391:104"/> giuen to a thouſand ſelect men, and called <hi>Milites, quaſi v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nusex mille,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Polib. lib. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>aut vnus mille valens,</hi> one out of a thouſand, or one worth a thouſand. The name of a ſouldier, is a name of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and labour, ſaith <hi>Polibius.</hi> In making choyce of ſouldiers the ancient Romans did chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerue two things. Firſt, they were carefull,<note place="margin">Non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te modeſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, quam virtutem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudinem deſidero. Caeſ. de bel. Gal. lib. 7.</note> that they were young, generouſly and vertuouſly enclyned. <hi>Iuuentus dat vires, virtus idoneum militem facit, &amp; verecundia dum prohibet fugere ſepe facit eſſe victoerm:</hi> the one giues ſtrength, the other addes courage, the champion of victory.<note place="margin">Veget. lib. q. cap.</note> Secondly, ſuch as were elected had their oath (by <hi>Lucius Flauius</hi> and <hi>Caius Varro</hi>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:17391:104"/> Conſuls) theſe words, <hi>iurabant ſe fugae, aut formidinis cauſa non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituros, neque ex ordine receſſuros, niſi teli petendi aut hoſtis feriendi cauſa, aut ciuis ſeruandi;</hi> that they ſhould not goe away, or leaue their ſtations, except to take vp a dart, hurt an enemy, or ſaue a friend. This oath was thoght ſo neceſſary, that <hi>ſine electione nemo conſcribebatur; ſic ſine ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento nemo nomen militis aut offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium ſorti us eſt:</hi> as without ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction none were enrolled: ſo without the oath, none did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the name or place of a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier. <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> ſending his ſonne to the warres vnder the command of <hi>Pompilio,</hi> did by his letters ſollicite, that hee ſhould not bee admitted vnto
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:17391:105"/> the army till hee had taken his oath; and his reaſon was, <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem non credebat niſi eum qui ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento in militiam conſecratur; vt Deo primum fides debita, deinde Principi &amp; reipublicae ſeruetur in columis.</hi> Becauſe he did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue any worthy the name of a ſouldier, but ſuch who by their oath had conſecrated themſelues to warre-farre, that their faith to God and loyalty to their Princes might be ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſerued. In this election the making choyce of forraine auxiliary ſouldiers, hath beene by many debated, and by ſome iniuſtly altogether diſabled: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom I do the rather diſſent, becauſe I do finde both in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and moderne warres that
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:17391:105"/> forraine helpes haue with the like (if not with greater) valour and faith mantained their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, then the natiues: yea I may ſafely affirme; that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine courage &amp; ſtrength hath repaired the loſſes of ſuch Princes and ſtates, who now alloweth their merite no other Chronicles then their owne wounds: howſoeuer,<note place="margin">Nichol. Match. in Princip.</note> that <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiuell</hi>-like inference of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Matchiuell</hi> doth not hold good, wherein (to diſproue the helpe of alients) hee preſents <hi>Dauid</hi> vpon the ſtage, refuſing <hi>Saules</hi> armes to fight with <hi>Goliah:</hi> but certainly <hi>Dauid</hi> was encouraged by an higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then all the ſubtillty of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiuels</hi> wit could reach: and if
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:17391:106"/> he had not (vpholden by that ſame power) beene more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in his owne armes, hee would not haue refuſed <hi>Saules</hi> offer. But becauſe I doe make haſte to ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of military diſcipline, I will onely recommend theſe cautions to Princes in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of auxiliary ſtrangers. Firſt, that they admit no moe, then they ſtand in neede of, may command, and are able without mutinity to keepe in pay. Next, that they chooſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch neighbouring Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys as ſtands well affected to their ſtate.<note place="margin">Ioſeph lib. 1. Auli. Pius 2. apud Plat. lib. 2.</note> Theſe two obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations beeing kept Princes may ſafely (if their owne forces bee not ſufficient)
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:17391:106"/> make election of forraine ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes.</p>
               <p>Next, vnto the election of ſuch whoſe bodyes,<note place="margin">Veget. lib. 9 Val. lib. 1</note> mindes and fayth are anſwerable to their charge: the ſecond care is, that by diſcipline they may be made skilfull, conformable to good lawes, and obedient to the commaund of their Princes. This military diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt chiefly,<note place="margin">Aug. apud Diog. lib. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitatione, in abdicatione volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, in cohibitione commeſſationum rapinarum otij &amp; innobedientiae.</hi> By exerciſe ſoldiers becom skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their armes, ſtrong in their bodyes, and couragious in their mindes.<note place="margin">Demet.</note> 
                  <hi>In omni prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, non tam multitudo &amp; virtus indocta quam ars &amp; exercitium
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:17391:107"/> ſolent praeſtare victoriam:</hi> Oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times skill and exerciſe effect more in warre then multitude or vertue without skill. On the contrary,<note place="margin">Socra. apud Stob. Zenon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Diog. lib. 7. Pith. in ſuis praecept.</note> idleneſſe (as it doth to all men) doth infect the bodyes and minds of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, with a ſenſleſſe ſecuritie, and dulneſſe to doe good, and ſtirres them vp to all ſuch vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as may offend others, and are the ſtaines of reputation and breach of good lawes; &amp; therefore great Captaines can neuer bee aſſured of exſpected ſucceſſe, without keeping of ſouldiers in dayly exerciſe. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Aſia</hi> had no vſe of ſhips yet leſt the ſouldiers might be dulled or corrupted by idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, order was giuen to build
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:17391:107"/> ſhips: for (one wittily ſayth) <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſanus otioſus, quam febricitans multo miſerior eſt:</hi> a man that is in health idle is in a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous eſtate, then he that is in an ague.</p>
               <p>Secondly, luxury of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers makes them become ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of reputation, effeminate and ſoft, and is to be choaked in the birth, leſt enchanting <hi>Circes</hi> change <hi>Vliſſes</hi> followers into ſwine: or luxurious <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pania,</hi> blemiſh the famous vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> and in the end deliuer him vp as a ſubiect to adorne the Trophes of his moſt contemned enemies.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by diſcipline ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers are to be reſtrained from rapes, ryots, and diſorders. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:17391:108"/> Cato</hi> did enact that the hand of him that committed theft, ſhould be cut off. <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> that whoſoeuer did offer iniury, ryots, or abandon his place without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, ſhould be ſeuerely puniſhed. <hi>Manlius Torquatus filium quod ipſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante ad dimicandum diſcenderat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Val. Max.</note> 
                  <hi>mactari iuſsit ſatius iudicans pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem forte filio, quam patria mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari diſciplina carere:</hi> This great Captaine did preferre the care of diſcipline to his victorious ſonne: but as in all other rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous execution of Iuſtice: ſo in military diſcipline ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is to be inflicted, firſt, <hi>Emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandi cauſa,</hi> that the party puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed may be therby bettred: for
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:17391:108"/> ſometimes ſeuerity cutteth off many, that thereafter might proue profitable members in the body of an army.<note place="margin">Veget. lib. 5 Plat. Epiſt.</note> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeuerity is to bee vſed, <hi>cum dignitas eius in quem peccatur tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda eſt, ne pretermiſſa animaduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio contemptum pariat:</hi> When neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of puniſhment begetteth contempt againſt the perſon of commanders and good lawes. Thirdly,<note place="margin">Saluſt: ad Caeſ. de rem ord.</note> puniſhment muſt haue its force, <hi>vt metu penae ceteri terreantur,</hi> that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amplary puniſhment vpon corrupt and vncurable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers may terrefie others.</p>
               <p>The neceſſitie of military diſcipline is demonſtrate,<note place="margin">Pub. Mim.</note> by the benefite that commeth to
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:17391:109"/> Princes by it, and by the loſſes that idleneſſe confuſion, &amp; the neglect thereof doe beget, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Macedo exiguam manum militarem a patre ſuſcepit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Val. Max. Quin. Curt</note> 
                  <hi>ſed do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam, qua aſuefacta militiae orbem terrarum aggreſſus, innumeras ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtium ſtrages fudit:</hi> the ſmall but skilfull force that <hi>Alexander</hi> did receiue from his father, did challenge the whole world, and ſubdue infinite number of enemies. The Romane Empire was begun, augmented, and continued by military diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and obſeruation of good lawes,<note place="margin">Polib. lib. 6. cap. 7.</note> vtterly euerted by luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, idleneſſe, and the like, conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming plagues. The fearefull name of <hi>Xerxes</hi> (by fooliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence)
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:17391:109"/> was ecclipſed by two ſhamefull ouerthrowes giuen him at <hi>Thermopilas</hi> &amp; <hi>Salamine,</hi> where too late hee did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, <hi>Se habere multos homines raro autem diſciplina tenaces.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XXIIII.</hi> Of the meditation and preparation of Princes againſt the day of death.</head>
               <p>AS there is nothing more certain the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deaths neuer failing arreſt, neither more irreconciliable terrible &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous enemy to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> then death:<note place="margin">Greg. Mor. 18.</note>
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:17391:110"/> So is there no more heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing care, then the watchful at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance for death, no truer badge of fortitude then the couragious defiance of death, &amp; no ſuch glorious victory as in the triumph ouer death.</p>
               <p>This due meditation &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of death is the Anuill whereon the armes that muſt conquer him are forged.<note place="margin">Bernard. Moral. 18.</note> The victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ouercomming of death is the crowne of a good life here,<note place="margin">Aug. de mort.</note> and the earneſt of aſſured happineſſe hereafter; and ought to be common to all men and proper to Princes. Firſt, leaſt greatneſſe, honours, riches, power, or other deceitfull va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities tranſport them, &amp; make
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:17391:110"/> them forgetfull of human con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition inuegle the eyes of their ſoules with ſecurity of long life, or make the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of death bitter, <hi>O mors quam amara eſt memoria tua homini pacem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benti in ſulſtantijs ſuis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouerb. 8.31. Eclleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> (who had long enioyed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, riches, and whatſoeuer elſe might dignifie and exalt him) did in end draw the ſhort concluſion, that all things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen are <hi>vanitas vanitatis,</hi> that the onely true comfort in this earthly kingdome is in exſpectation of a better hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and that the ſoule ſtaruing-pleaſures after which he had formerly hungred, were but vanities and vexation of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. When ſickeneſſe or old age
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:17391:111"/> (the harbengers of inexorable death) ſuch Princes to yeelde nature her due, they may thus meditate and reaſon with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues:<note place="margin">Aegritudo &amp; ſenectus mortis nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij ſunt. Chryſ. hom 5.</note> death is not to be feared where a good life hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the way: to heare of death is no nouelty: that they with al men are borne to dye: that all their aunceſtors are by death diſſolued: what numbers of Monarchs are before them, &amp; that all ſhall follow them: that death is the end of miſeries, &amp; entry to true happineſſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where incorrupt treaſure abides them: that the mercie-Maſter the true Samaritan, and great Phyſition of ſoules hath a ſalue for euery ſore; that hee did cure the woman whoſe
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:17391:111"/> faith was great, ſaued his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles whoſe faith was little and hath promiſed (by the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of the Muſtard ſeed) to receiue in his kingdome the widdowes mite,<note place="margin">Math. 8.25.26.13.31. Si poſſemus ſuper talem aſcendere ſpeculum de quo vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam terram ſub pedibus cerneremus iam tibi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenderem mundi rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, reges regibus, regna regnis colliſa: alios torqueri, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios necari alios abſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri flucti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, alios in ſeruitutem trahi, hic nuptias illi. planctum illos naſci iſtos mori. Hieron. ad Heled.</note> or the leaſt dram of ſauing faith. To theſe meditations may be added the weakeneſſe, ſhortnes and frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the life of man, ſubiect to ſickneſſe, pouerty, iniuries, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and millions of downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing miſeries: yea miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man is dayly tormented with the chief pleaſures of life. Delicacy of meates begetteth cruditie &amp; indigeſtion; ſtrong drinke palſie and trembling; luſt, ſtupidity, weakning of the body: riches enuy in poſſeſſing of them, and ſorrow in leauing
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:17391:112"/> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: in one word, euery Ioy hath his enſuing ſorrow, life is blinde, doubtfull and full of troubles; honors ſwelleth it, ſorrow extenuates it, heate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicates it, ſurfets oppreſſe it, ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe conſumes it, ſolitude im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſons it, ſecurity duls it, yong age exalts it, youth profuſeth it, old age makes it feeble, and death ruines it: what a fooliſh frailty is it then to feare death, when in each or moſt of theſe calamities of life, we wiſh death ſhould ceaſe vpon vs.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſeeing the body of man is but the ruinous cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage wherein the ſoule of man is impriſoned, and dayly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted with neuer ceaſing enemies: the beſt way to auoyd
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:17391:112"/> a more glorious &amp; ſure dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place for ſo heauenly a gueſt, is timely to teach the ſoule to deſpiſe the body, that ſhe hath no intereſt in it; is a ſtranger, a pilgrime, and a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried gueſt, trauelling towards her long wiſhed home, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly detained within the dungeon of corrupt fleſh: that becauſe death is the way wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe muſt arriue at her long wiſhed heauen, ſhee muſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly acquaint her ſelfe with death; to diſcouer the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ambuſcadoes, and enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring traps that are hidden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ouerſhadowing groues of greatneſſe and proſperitie.</p>
               <p>This ſerious meditation of death, the familiar conuerſing with
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:17391:113"/> death, and timely diſiunction of the ſoule from the body is the right preparation to dye, and when death comes, boldly with a kingly courage, trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly demand him in the face, <hi>Death where is thy ſting? Maximilian</hi> the Emperour cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his tombe fiue yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death be carried wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hee did goe,<note place="margin">Ex orat. fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neb. Sueu.</note> that by the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of death he might diſlodge ambitious, fooliſh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, wordly, affections, and be ready with old Swan-ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Simeon</hi> to receiue his ſafe conduct,<note place="margin">Luc. 2.25.26.27.28.29.30.</note> and ſay, <hi>Now Lord let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou thy ſeruant depart im peace for mine eyes haue ſeene my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, death is carefully
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:17391:113"/> to be premeditated, becauſe the forgetfulneſſe of death increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the horror, and augments the feare of vnexſpected death.<note place="margin">Aug. de mort.</note> 
                  <hi>Omnia repentina grauiora ſunt, ſed premeditatio futurorum malorum lenit eorum aduentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This conſideration of the vncertainety and vnexſpected comming of death and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouiſion for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming is able to withſtand the furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſſaults of fearefull rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious fleſh,<note place="margin">Petrar. dial. 28.</note> ambition and down throwing pride of the moſt powerfull Princes;<note place="margin">Luc. 21.29. Theſſ. 1.5. Reuel. 3.3.</note> is a carefull ſeruant for the comming of the maſter: a neuer ſleeping watch, attending the theefe &amp; a prouident <hi>Oeconomus</hi> for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp of true ſtore. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:17391:114"/> O king, ſayde <hi>Agapetus</hi> to <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> that death feares not the ſpenldor of honour or greatneſſe,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.7.</note> but impartially d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uoures Kings and Beggers: therefore before his comming lay vp prouiſion in heauen where no corruption ſhall haue entry but ſhall returne to duſt &amp; aſhes from whence it did come,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.21.7.5.</note> and man borne naked ſhall goe hence naked, death ſhall finde him as life leaues him, and iudgement ſhall finde him as death leaues him.<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. de doct thiſt. Lact. lib. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Non poteſt male mori qui bene vixit &amp; plerunque mala mors eſt, quam mala vita praeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, nam ſicut vita ipſa bonum eſt cum virtute viuitur malum ſi cum ſcelere; Ita &amp; mors ex prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritis
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:17391:114"/> vitae actibus ponderanda eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTIO. XXV.</hi> Of mourning for the dead, and of Chriſtian and Princely burials.</head>
               <p>LEt ſuch Critickes who condemne mourning ſermons,<note place="margin">Chriſtiano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum iuſtoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defunctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corpora (quibus ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ad bona opera vſus eſt ſpiritus ſanctus) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficioſa pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate curanda exequtae cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrand ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſunt. Aug. in Pat.</note> and funeral ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to the praiſe of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full departed; conſider that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or ſingularity is the mother of their errour, and as it is true, that Chriſtians tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from this life: <hi>Non ſunt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsi ſed praemiſsi,</hi> ſo is it as true <hi>fidelibus defunctis debito honore ac funebri oratione parentare, nulla vnquam pietas aut religio vetuit.</hi>
                  <pb n="210" facs="tcp:17391:115"/> The redoubled groanes of our Sauiour at the death of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> demonſtrate that mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the dead is a true ſigne of the pietie of the liuing.<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.33 38.</note> 
                  <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phani Martyrium maximis Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anorum planctibus &amp; gemitibus fuit coronatum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 8.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieremias</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle the death of king <hi>Icſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> in the aſſembly of the people. <hi>Abraham</hi> his wife <hi>Sarah:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 23.2.</note> the whole houſe of Iſrael did mourne for <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> thirty dayes.<note place="margin">Deut. 29.8.</note> King <hi>Dauid</hi> did lament for the death of <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> his ſonne,<note place="margin">Sam. 2.19.18.</note> and for the death of <hi>Saul</hi> his enemy. The holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did bemone the death of their Princes and others their friends. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did moſt rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly garniſh the hearſe of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>
                  <pb n="211" facs="tcp:17391:115"/> with a learned Sermon and eloquent oration. <hi>Gregorius Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzenus mortuum fratre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Caeſariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laudauit eiuſque memoriam poſteris funebri oratione commendauit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. de Sepul. Hier. in pan.</note> 
                  <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome Damaſcen</hi> and all the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent pillars of the Church did honourably regard the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and laſt honors done to the Chriſtians deceaſed.</p>
               <p>I ceaſe to ſpeake of honors done to Princes after their death by the Phyloſophers and ancient heathen: it is dolefully regiſtred, that at the tragicall funerals of <hi>Achilles</hi> &amp; <hi>Patroclus</hi> killed by the <hi>Troians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Homer Illi.</note> 
                  <hi>Lachrimis non ſolum arma lugentium rigaren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed &amp; arenae quoque madeſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi> Old <hi>Solon</hi> did delight to bee beloued in his life time,
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:17391:116"/> that at his death the ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full complaints of his friends might accompany him to his graue.<note place="margin">Ex dic. Phil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Iulius Caeſar queſtor Iuliam Amitam vx remque Corneliam pro roſtris laudauit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All lawes doe warrant ſuch offices as are done at the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of ſuch as haue beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the commonwealth wherein they did liue, to be <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta &amp; iure acta,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuſt.</note> and the leaſt defacing of ſepulchers of the dead, or touch of reproach hath beene holden an offence of higher quality then the ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the houſes of the liuing or ſpoken againſt their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in their life time, <hi>In iuris prudentia quotieſcunque leges vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentium pugnant cum legibus
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:17391:116"/> po-ſthumilijs ſemper preualent post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humiae omniaque iuris priuilegia fulta fauore publico cedunt &amp; vincuntur ab vna ſola actione fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ancient Chriſtians did accompt it the extremity of perſecution that they were compelled <hi>(ſine ſupremo honore canticorum &amp; himnorum)</hi> to burie their dead in ſilence.<note place="margin">Dion. apud. Stob.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould exceede the limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted breuity that I haue enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to my ſelfe, if I ſhould recount the various and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious funerall rites obſerued amongſt the heathen, or the ſumptuous and vnprofitable charges beſtowed amongſt ſome Chriſtians. <hi>Egyptij condie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, Perſae cera circum linitos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debant
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:17391:117"/> mortuos eoſque domi ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant vt quam maxime permane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent diuturna corpora. Magoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mos erat non humare corpora, niſi a feris antea fuiſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlaniata. Meſſagetae cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natos &amp; propinquos mortuos deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ducentes honeſtius ac rectius a ſe quam a vermibus commedantur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I leaue the funerall fiers wherein anciently,<note place="margin">Sepulturae Pompa ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis eſt, Sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium vino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam mortuorum praeſidium. Aug. de cura promort.</note> and yet, the bodies of the dead haue beene and are conſumed to aſhes: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I ſpeake of the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iewells, rich clothes, gold, ſiluer, ſeruants, horſe, &amp; other conceited fooleries,<note place="margin">Ioan Boem. de morib. omn. gen-</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in diuers Nations, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are interred. I doe onely allow of ſuch honourable bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of Princes, as is obſerued amongſt Chriſtians, &amp; which
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:17391:117"/> is rather accompanied and condoled with the preſence and teares of al good ſubiects; ſermons funerall orations and charitable almes (thereby in citing the ſucceeding poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to imitate the vertues of the deceaſed prince) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defaced by ſuperſtitious rites or prodigall profuſion of ſuperfluous and vnprofitable charge. <hi>Eccleſia fulgeat in parietibus, ſed ne egeat in pauperibus, lapides auro indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur, non vt Eccleſiae filij nudi deſerantur:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:118"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>Page 2. marge capitum, perſuaſum. p. 11. line 16. r. &amp; l. 20. r. their p. 21. l. 15. r. ſapiunt. p. 23. l. 7. r. atergo. p. 25. l. 14. r. eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth. 26. l. 17. r. melancholius. p. 37. l. 20. 21. ſemper it. p. 45. l. 8. r. Alcinoique. p. 49. l. 6. r. proſunditas. l. 5. altitudo. p. 55. l. 13. r. contrahes. p. 62. l. 3. r. pictori. p. 63. l. 9. r. preeſſe. p. 92. l. 6. r. ad p. 98. l. 2. put out and. p. 100. l. 7. r. leges, p 183. l. 19. r. Marcellus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 148. l. 10. ſuperſtitious. p. 152. r. zelus. p. 172. l 4 r. Aenas and Turnus. 214. l. 1. r. condiebant. in marge r. viuorum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17391:118"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
